<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-04-07T22:35:00+12:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">.</title><entry><title type="html">My Yeah! playlist</title><link href="/2023/03/31/yeah-playlist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Yeah! playlist" /><published>2023-03-31T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2023-03-31T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>/2023/03/31/yeah-playlist</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/03/31/yeah-playlist.html"><![CDATA[<p>People often respond to crisis in strange ways, and my response to Covid lockdown, in March 2020, was to compile my first Spotify playlist.</p>

<p>Back in the 90s I was a very serious maker of mix tapes, but I didn’t take to mp3 playlists in quite the same way, and kind of fell out of the habit. The mp3 blog revolution also passed me by. But in March 2020, with the world in the grips of a Pandemic, I felt a strange need to sum up something about me, to coalesce a bunch of songs that felt like a bulwark to All That. And having a Spotify account, well I made a playlist.</p>

<p>I feel duty-bound to add that Spotify is also instrumental in the impoverishment of creators, but you know, if not them then some other company would be. The real tragedy is the advent of intangible digital media. No more reason to visit music shops, no more questing for obscure disks. We have everything everywhere all at once, but it’s not nearly as satisfying, somehow.</p>

<p>I know there’s something of a rebellion against that, with a vinyl and (against all logic) cassette tape revival, but I just don’t have the hipster energy to buy into that. The ship has sailed, it’s time to for all you can eat at the music buffet.</p>

<p>Moving on from that depressing aside, I have to say that that first lockdown was rather wonderful. It was great to have a chance from the usual madcap tedium of life, the weather was nice where I lived, and when we went for socially distanced walks everyone kept each other at arms’ length, which is how I’d prefer to have them. My wife overcompensated for the uncertainty with unconstrained grocery buying, so we feasted like kings.</p>

<p>I suppose I should acknowledge that in New Zealand covid was controlled relatively quickly, so the lockdown felt worthwhile. Not everyone had such a benign experience, and much of the planet went mad over the following two years, including New Zealand too, at the very end. But that first lockdown, I enjoyed it.</p>

<p>Back to the playlist: now these songs have a kind of spirt about them that induces a kind of gleeful mania that I call “Yeah!”. But while most of these songs have significance for me, but they aren’t necessarily my all time favourites. For example: California Uber Alles is a rollicking good time, but I’ve never checked out the band’s catalogue beyond their debut. To complicate things further, some tracks are from bands I do like but aren’t my favourites. And to cap it all many of my favourite groups (and composers) aren’t represented at all because they simply didn’t create the kind of music that stimulates yeahness in me. So this playlist is a kind of non-sequiteur slice of excitement that definitely represents something of me, without giving a sense of the totality of my musical taste whatsoever. I have a conceit that no algorithm monitoring my life’s listening could ever compute this playlist from this material, because yeahness is solely defined in my brain with no obvious external criteria. But in 2023 I don’t feel I can say it definitely won’t happen.</p>

<h1 id="the-playlist">The playlist</h1>

<h2 id="1-bauhaus---third-uncle-1982">1. Bauhaus - Third Uncle (1982)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sILbx5xbwPY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Third Uncle is a Brian Eno cover. The original is an art rock classic, but it feels a bit flabby compared to this Bauhaus do-over, which is a Plinian eruption of punk mania.</p>

<p>One of these days (God help you) I’ll write an essay on Bauhaus, who are an enduring wrong-headed pleasure. As well as writing many excellent, strange songs of their own, they did a sideline in glam rock covers. Two of note they did were T-Rex’s Telegram Sam, and Bowie’s Ziggy Stardust, which was released as a (Top 20 UK) single. All of these covers are (in my rather sacrilegious view) superior to the originals.</p>

<h1 id="2-tones-on-tail---go-1984">2. Tones on Tail - Go! (1984)</h1>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/L51SlSyZo1M" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Tones on Tail featured two Bauhaus alumni, and Go! has similar energy. More from them later.</p>

<h2 id="3-yellow-magic-orchestra---absolute-ego-dance-1979">3. Yellow Magic Orchestra - Absolute Ego Dance (1979)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YWgBvslg6I0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Probably a pretty unorthodox choice for a YMO track, but I like this song’s genial mania. Wheee!</p>

<p>RIP Sakamoto-san and Takahashi-san.</p>

<h2 id="4-james-holden---spinning-dance-2019">4. James Holden - Spinning Dance (2019)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/X1BgRaNFWeI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>We’ve had three post-punk/new wave fest, so let’s mix it up by zipping to the 21st century, to hear some weird jazzy neo pagan antics by one of modern electronica’s finest producers. Wordless groaning? Check! Bewildering changes in time signature? Absolutely! Hippie flute? Er, sure! Subliminal sparkling synthesis? Absolutely! Just ecstatic.</p>

<h2 id="5-the-black-dog---tahr-1995">5. The Black Dog - Tahr (1995)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IaO2hZT7YN0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This one conjures in my head a back alley chase on a desert world a thousand years from now. Glorious track.</p>

<h2 id="6-susumu-hirasawa---mediational-field-2006">6. Susumu Hirasawa - Mediational Field (2006)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/77WQdNbq9nQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This track was the opening theme for the late Satoshi Kon’s surreal anime masterpiece Paprika (which lamentably turned out to be Kon’s final film). Again, this track is very high energy, to the point where the mix is (to my humble ear) a touch oversaturated, but it’s a perfect intro to the movie’s bonkers world.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Susumu_Hirasawa">Hirasawa</a>’s work is worth expanding on. Originally an art/punk/synth rocker in P-Model, a group that could be described as “YMOish”, he evolved in the 90s into a singing electronica producer. He provided the score for several of Kon’s movies, and perhaps most memorably for songs on the soundtracks for the Berserk anime (sadly not available on Spotify). I’m usually happy enough with atrocious singers like Morrissey or Ian Curtis, but Hirasawa really has an astonishing voice.</p>

<h2 id="7-james-holden---lump-2006">7. James Holden - Lump (2006)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2jKwkou34Oo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A bravura piece of disorienting, gritty dance-o-tronica. The robot’s circuits are malfunctioning.</p>

<h2 id="8-david-bowie---moonage-daydream-1972">8. David Bowie - Moonage Daydream (1972)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/RPUAldgS7Sg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This probably doesn’t need much introduction, it’s a classic rocker. My favourite bit is the line:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Put your space face close to mine, love
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>When I first heard the song I misheard space face as “space bass”, which made me immediately think of Bootsy Collins.</p>

<h2 id="9-bauhaus---god-in-an-alcove-1980">9. Bauhaus - God in an Alcove (1980)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/T-zxj8dgG9s" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This song is a ball of sinewy fury, and, well, “so silly”. “Silly, silly, silly”, etc. Great guitar and bass work and wonky low fi synth drums… well, the whole band’s great, really.</p>

<h2 id="10-a-certain-ratio---shack-up-1980">10. A Certain Ratio - Shack Up (1980)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JARiW_qvRqo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I have a soft spot for early ACR. This song’s a northern soul cover, with the scratchy funk arrangement weirdly undercut by Joy Division-esque vocals. The rhythm section and the slightly rancid guitar make it for me.</p>

<h2 id="11-can---mother-sky-edit-1970">11. Can - Mother Sky (edit) (1970)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/4C4PwoZLGT8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>A grand old juggernaut, Jaki pounding away on the skins, Holger plucking out a two note bassline, Damo intoning whatever it is he’s intoning. And Irmin’s Irmining. Classic.</p>

<h2 id="12-holly-herndon---frontier-2019">12. Holly Herndon - Frontier (2019)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rvNqNgHAEys" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Speaking of Spotify, I first heard this on the work Sonos. The music in our office is pretty dire, really, and I’ve often tried to fight the blandom by playing something with personality. (One time I managed to play Chopin for an afternoon, which went alright. Another time I tried playing The Shamen’s Boss Drum album, and someone switched it off halfway through the first song. Philistines!) Just generally people play colourless “lo fi” hip hop or inocuous light funk/jazz. I mean sure, you can’t put on Einsturzende Neubauten in the office or people will get upset, but still… better if it didn’t exist at all really. Most of us wear headphones anyway.</p>

<p>But one day, out of the blue, in the office I heard Frontier, and I was so taken I had to check out what it was. And a couple of hours later I had worked my way through Holly Herndon’s entire discography. I was moved enough to eventually buy Frontier’s parent album, which I think is an excellent collection reminiscent (to me at least) of Laurie Anderson’s Big Science.</p>

<p>The arrangement is mostly voices - real and synthetic - and drums. It’s another paganish piece full of tension, with a wonderful climax at the end. I first heard Frontier perhaps a month before Covid hit, and it became for me linked to the pandemic, and a big motivator for building this playlist. It’s a strange song for strange times.</p>

<h2 id="13-roxy-music---virginia-plain-1972">13. Roxy Music - Virginia Plain (1972)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jg9b2PnmgxY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This is such a joyful song, everyone just thrashing about for three minutes. The highlight for me is Brian Eno’s repeated three note synth “solo”. On paper it’s a bit pathetic, but with his, well, <em>Enoesque</em> treatments it has a kind of understated cool.</p>

<h2 id="14-can---halleluwah-edit-1971">14. Can - Halleluwah (edit) (1971)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ld-JTtvQZq8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Maybe everyone’s favourite Can song? The drumming is just majestic, the lyrics are inscrutable, and the jamming reveals unexpected details. It’s an utterly unique work.</p>

<h2 id="15-harmonia---watussi-1974">15. Harmonia - Watussi (1974)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iQs07Sofu8I" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This is perhaps the piece of music dearest to my heart. From the first time my friend Michael played it to me, more than 20 years ago, it’s sounded to me like the apotheosis of everything I love about 1970s electronic music. It feels like the future, but also intimately like childhood… It’s sort of hard to explain. More objectively it’s archetypal, the refined aspirations of the Krautrock movement. It’s the closest thing I’ve ever heard to my conception of aesthetic, sonic, philosophical perfection. Well, hope you like it!</p>

<h2 id="16-plaid---abla-eedio-1997">16. Plaid - Abla Eedio (1997)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JaXlXI-VOYI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The Plaid duo had left the Black Dog, but for this track, on their first post-Black-Dog album, the Black Dog hadn’t yet left Plaid. A restless, urgent, weird rhythm periodically pierced by dramatic chord stabs. Superb. Plaid have had an odd career, essentially piling up innumerable editions of about three or four track archetypes. They never produced another one like this, though, which is a shame. In this case, redundancy would be good.</p>

<h2 id="17-the-art-of-noise---close-to-the-edit-1984">17. The Art of Noise - Close to the Edit (1984)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WnungT4zGOM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The hiatus from manic music ends here… Forty years on it’s hard to understand how revolutionary this song felt at the time, but it really was. I think the track’s chief merit is how conventionless it is. As a kind of lockstep conformity later developed with house and techno in the later 80s, the Art of Noise got left behind. (There’s a series of wonderful mid 80s electronic danceish albums produced using the Fairlight CMI: Cabaret Voltaire’s Microphonies, Jean Michel Jarre’s Zoolook, and Depeche Mode’s Construction Time Again. While these albums might have enough in common to be their own genre, maybe, they left no immediate descendents and were essentially marooned in the mid 80s. Shame really.)</p>

<h2 id="18-tones-on-tail---theres-only-one-1982">18. Tones on Tail - There’s only one (1982)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bzRuVK92AAo" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It’s hard to categorise this madness, but kudos to Daniel Ash’s guitar work. If there’s one word to describe the song, it’s “hurtling”.</p>

<h2 id="19-joy-division---dead-souls-1979">19. Joy Division - Dead Souls (1979)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mKWHa65cmns" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>“They keep calling me!” bellows Ian. “Yeah, right on”, I yell back. Can’t believe it was only a B side.</p>

<h2 id="20-dead-kennedys---california-uber-alles-1980">20. Dead Kennedys - California Uber Alles (1980)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jrWflCJPM4w" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>We’re 20 tracks in, so how about some Dead Kennedys? Probably the most energy out of any song here. The secret of this song is that although DK were punk, and they certainly pour petrol on it, it’s really a surf rock number. The lyrics about hippie totalitarianism are amusingly dated, yet still strangely relevant… From the same album I also love “Holiday in Cambodia”, from the same album. And also, er, “Too Drunk to Fuck”.</p>

<h2 id="21-donna-summer---i-feel-love-1977">21. Donna Summer - I feel love (1977)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/B2qI6UDD2uQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Another song that’s the future. Giorgio’s sequencer does most of the talking, while Donna’s cooing does the rest.</p>

<h2 id="22-the-orb---toxygene-1997">22. The Orb - Toxygene (1997)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mz2eGSv7EkM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>By the Orb’s fourth album, Orblivion, the band were well off their earlier pace, but Toxygene represented one last hurrah, a furious barn stormer of a track.</p>

<h2 id="23-sisters-of-mercy---jolene-1983">23. Sisters of Mercy - Jolene (1983)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2ymbfKceRto" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I suspect Sisters fans will find it disgraceful I picked this track over any number of worthier ones, but this dodgy cover just makes me laugh, and comes from the early period when Andrew Eldritch didn’t take himself too seriously. Having a man singing what was originally a female part adds a bit of an amusing gay overtone to procedings, but what I love most is the inconcruous chugging guitars and Eldritch’s stentorian delivery.</p>

<p>Another anecdote: back when I was in my teens I dubbed this track off another dub (probably off bootleg vinyl) I borrowed from a friend. Now in those days making dub of a dub was considered a bit disreputable, because cassette tape is a pretty degraded format, so multi-generational copies are pretty rubbish. Because the original recording was lo-fi to start with, the dub’s distortion sort of warped the sound in a way that actually improved it. (A similar situation was when, through poverty, I was reduced to listening to my walkman on mono headphones, and I found that Nevermind sounded gruntier that way.)</p>

<p>Finally, I love Reptile House from the same period.</p>

<h2 id="24-adam-ant---dog-eat-dog-1980">24. Adam Ant - Dog Eat Dog (1980)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Z5WNZxoTnAA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I didn’t pay any attention to Adam Ant until very recently, but he was quite the phenomenon. I still struggle to understand how a song with an arrangement as uncommercial as Prince Charming managed to get to number 1, but that was the genius of Ant and his age. Dog Eat Dog has a bit more bite (hoho!) than subsequent tracks, when Adam really leaned into his pantomime persona, so this one gets my pick. (Honourable mention: the Link Wray “homage” Killer in the Home, from the same album.)</p>

<h2 id="25-the-smiths---the-queen-is-dead-1986">25. The Smiths - The Queen is Dead (1986)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fs5j3NgEDxs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This is far from being my favourite Smiths song, but it is the most relentless. The rhythm section is blistering, and Johnny’s as majestic as ever. Meanwhile Moz’s lyrics and singing floats somewhere between new Dylan profundity and just pissing about.</p>

<h2 id="26-a-certain-ratio---do-the-du-casse-1980">26. A Certain Ratio - Do the Du (Casse) (1980)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TsJ_54WyZ48" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>It’s got the same rhythm and chord relationship as the Knightrider theme, so clearly that bodes well, but these lyrics:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>My heart was just an open sore
That you picked at, till it was raw
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><em>chef’s kiss</em></p>

<p>I do have a thing about early ACR. The song Flight, though slower and more otherworldly, could also easily be on this compilation.</p>

<h2 id="26-james-brown---soul-power-1970">26. James Brown - Soul Power (1970)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UM9pqMqHCQ0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>He’s got to have it, you know. Shout out to Bootsy, whose bass playing is <em>magnifique</em>.</p>

<h2 id="28-funkadelic---standing-on-the-verge-of-getting-it-on-1973">28. Funkadelic - Standing on the Verge of Getting it On (1973?)</h2>

<p>Speaking of Bootsy, let’s move on to the P-Funk milieu. All hail <del>Discordia</del>George Clinton! This particular song is, well, furiously horny… While I’m here, let’s salute some of the silliest and most profound lyrics in the P-Funk canon:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>I have tasted the maggots in the mind of the universe...
I was not offended.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>and</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Everybody's got a little light under the sun
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>and</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>We love to funk you Funkenstein
Your funk is the best!
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="29-public-enemy---revolutionary-generation-1990">29. Public Enemy - Revolutionary Generation (1990)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s9AeoAVmRIA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I’m not the biggest hiphop fan, at least of hiphop past about 1993, but I have maximum respect Public Enemy and the raw fury of the Bomb Squad’s productions. This song is a righteous paean to Black women (somewhat against the flow of hip hop tradition), which absolutely kitchen sinks it from beginning to end.</p>

<h2 id="30-the-klf---what-time-is-love-live-at-trancentral-1990">30. The KLF - What time is Love? Live at Trancentral (1990)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HY1SVaT8gV0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The KLF’s oeuvre wasn’t added to Spotify until 2021, but this track, a grand old acid house warhorse, makes for a welcome addition. Pure Trance purists will prefer the 1988 original, but this successful retooling was a template for the KLF’s remarkable achievements and hijinks in 1991.</p>

<h2 id="31-suicide---ghost-rider-1977">31. Suicide - Ghost Rider (1977)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dn7SBQ6X5HU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This is definitely the most minimal yeah! song in this comp, but the commencement of the motorik three note sequence never ceases to rouse my passion. I’d always thought the song had no percussion, but just listening back just now I noticed a fairly discreet kick pulse. Who knew?</p>

<p>I’ve never been quite sure of where I stand on Alan Vega’s Elvis-having-a-seizure singing, but I guess it served to put off squares. It’s strange to hear a song that’s not at all rock and roll and yet utterly rock and roll.</p>

<h2 id="32-aphex-twin---green-calx-1985---1992">32. Aphex Twin - Green Calx (~1985 - ~1992)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YbIu9hXMggg" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>My favourite Aphex Twin album is Selected Ambient Works ‘85 - ‘92 - in fact the only other album from him that doesn’t aggravate me is Syro 25 years later. As for Green Calx, it isn’t ambient in the slighest; instead it’s a majestic acid banger.</p>

<h2 id="33-orchestral-maneouvres-in-the-dark---radio-waves-1983">33. Orchestral Maneouvres in the Dark - Radio Waves (1983)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Evas4RwWg-I" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>I have a massive softspot for OMD, even if they’re a bit naff. This enconium to electromagnetic energy bounds along like a jolly labrador (and with about as much brains). I highly recommend its parent album, Dazzleships.</p>

<h2 id="34-japan---life-in-tokyo-1979">34. Japan - Life in Tokyo (1979)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/O0x4XHdoQ9E" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>“Oh - oh - oh life can be cruel.” Not sure if there’s a song more 1979, with the Moroder-produced phased sequencer line, and David Sylvian’s hair (soon to be “emulated” by Duran Duran). Mick Karn (RIP)’s erotic(!) bass work is the chief delight.</p>

<p>This is as good a point as any to give an honourable mention to Gary Numan’s Cars, which is kind of a “Yeah!” song, but somehow in my head not quite.</p>

<h2 id="35-the-black-dog---end-of-time-1995">35. The Black Dog - End of Time (1995)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/imN0xSVZF0s" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Coming at the end of Warp’s golden age of “IDM”, Spanners is my favourite album of that genre, probably because it isn’t very representative (not too-cool like Aphex Twin, nor scornful like Autechre). End of Time is a UFO joyride near the end of Spanners.</p>

<p>I’m still a bit grief-stricken Spanners was the group’s last outing before splitting into Plaid and a one man Black Dog (Ken Downie). Thirty years later Plaid, though never less than immaculate, is just going through the motions, while the Black Dog bangs out solid but largely miserablist techno and ambient. Well, age shall not wither Spanners, nor the rush of End of Time.</p>

<h2 id="36-plaid---at-last-2011">36. Plaid - At Last (2011)</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BaCon7HjCAI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Yeah! songs don’t feel very concludey to me - they’re a bit like an alarm clock being used to get a baby to sleep. So cap off this excursion I’ve picked the highly apt At Last, as a very decent - if not highly energetic - finale.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[People often respond to crisis in strange ways, and my response to Covid lockdown, in March 2020, was to compile my first Spotify playlist.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One after 929</title><link href="/2023/01/27/lego.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One after 929" /><published>2023-01-27T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2023-01-27T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>/2023/01/27/lego</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/01/27/lego.html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an account of my personal love affair with Lego and model LL928.</p>

<h1 id="928">928</h1>

<p>It all started around about 1981 when I started getting lego sets. I was 5-6 years old and anything coming into contact with my senses felt extremely vivid. (Memories from that time remain similarly sharp - there might not be many of them, but they’re intense. From my subjective viewpoint, these memories are the most valuable things I have. I imagine all people experience something similar with childhood memories, although it’s not something we often talk about.)</p>

<p>While the first, modest Lego sets my brother and I received were cool, there were greater riches to be spied in the annual Lego catalogues we’d sometimes acquire. Seeing dioramas of many sets on display - whole cities on display - provided the feel of another world: an idealised (Danish) city peopled with friendly automatons. Lego “society” seemed so uncomplicated and idea; no one would ever swear or spit or be alcoholic or mentally ill. (All this was, of course, satirised very effectively in the first Lego Movie.)</p>

<p>What attracted me more than life on Lego Earth, however, was the possibility and promise of Lego space. The Lego Space sets looked amazing, and in toy shops I loved scanning the boxes showing rocket ships in front of Star Trek backgrounds. These scenes felt remote but again, cosmically benign.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/Classic_Space_1979-560x272.jpg" alt="1979 space lego catalogue" title="1979 space lego catalogue" />
    <figcaption>The 1979 space lego catalogue</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Around 1982 my friend Kevin got one of the larger space sets, 924. This was part of a series of three spaceship models: 918, 924, and 928. These were all variations of the same blue and grey spaceship archetype (reminiscent but of course legally distinct from a Star Destroyer from Star Wars). 924 was pretty cool; it had a little cargo bay. But the set that really impressed me was the big daddy of the series, 928, sporting four grey rocket engines, compared to 924’s two and 918’s one. When my grandparents went on holiday to Australia in 1983, my mother arranged, at my behest for them to fetch back 928, duty free.</p>

<p>When they returned to Wellington some weeks later (in a short-bodied 747, landing at Wellington airport, can you imagine it?!), it turned out 928 was no longer being produced.Instead they picked up 6980, 928’s grand successor. (So expensive was the set that it was supposed to be my birthday <em>and</em> Christmas present combined. My parents seemed to have forgotten this come December, luckily.)</p>

<p>Now 6980 was a pretty decent set (lucky boy, so much privilege, etc), and it did have more going on than 928 (a detachable lab, a twin cockpit, and what looked like four cannons at the front). And yet, somehow for me it lacked the angular, solid seriousness of the earlier dreadnaught. So 928 remained lodged in a more wistful ventricle of my heart, and for many years afterwards (indeed, even into my late teens!) I would periodically to buy the most faithful of version of 928 I could from the lego pieces I had. I did a decent job, but I was never going to get there. 6980 turned out to be the last set of lego I had as a child. Thinking about it now, I’m not sure if my parents felt I already had enough, or if I lost interest in acquiring more. Probably a bit of both.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/6980.jpg" alt="Space lego model 6980" title="Space lego model 6980" />
    <figcaption>Space lego model 6980 - grand, but not quite the same.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Not much happened for nearly 40 years, until my son Angus appeared on the scene and attained lego age. With each set he received I’d pine out loud for 928, and my highly practical wife Sally’s set about combing of trading sites for old space lego in the hope of spotting 928. Eventually a set of assorted space lego bricks came up, and we spied components from 928. To be honest I felt like it was a bit too late; to get the most out of 928, I really ought to be 8 years old. For Sally though, Angus could get that experience, and enjoy building with his Dad, so she bought the set. Our instincts were correct and from the pieces we were able to assemble a largely complete 928 set, shown below.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/928.jpg" alt="Space lego model 928" title="Space lego model 928" />
    <figcaption>Space lego model 928 - get out of my dreams, and onto my dining table.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>So, what’s it like the assembling the lego set of your dreams 40 years later? Well, I have to say there wasn’t much in the way of euphoria or triumph. Angus and I built the set over a couple of hours, and then it was done. Was it everything I dreamed? Yes, but you feel a bit differently when you’re 46 than when you’re 6. The set is nice to have a look at, but it lacks the romantic misery of not getting what you want. It doesn’t feel like mine, more like I’ve borrowed it for the moment. That said, I do get some satisfaction sometimes by briefly walking around my living room with it making <em>psshew</em> noises.</p>

<h1 id="929">929</h1>

<p>But Sally didn’t stop there. Still keeping an eye on the second hand sites, Benny’s Spaceship from the Lego Movie, came up for sale, and she saw fit to buy it as a Christmas project for Gus and me. This ship sports “LL929” along the sides of its fuselage as a nod to 928, will henceforth be known as 929.</p>

<p>I found the character of Benny in the Lego Movie a little frustrating. I mean, it was nice he was there to represent classic Space Lego (although he should have worn the OG red or white spacesuit; the blue spacesuit came several years later.) And I didn’t like his spaceship. While referencing 928, it lacked the clean lines and was much too busy and festooned with crap. I would have preferred he was just flying 928 itself!</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/929.jpg" alt="Lego model '929'" title="Lego model '929'" />
    <figcaption>Lego model '929' - busy</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Having built 929, I have to row back some of my criticisms. Although it certainly is festooned with crap, it’s well thought out crap, much of it nods to other classic space lego sets. And the set many moving parts, and is highly playable: there’s two sets of missile launchers, and even a couple of mini-fighters attached at the tip of each wing. The rococo ornamentation on the ship does have benefits. The second-hand set we bought had a few pieces missing, but with so much greebley carry on on the surface, it’s really hard to tell that some of it is not there.</p>

<h1 id="10497">10497</h1>

<p>For its 90th anniversary in 2022 Lego brought out 10497, a tribute to 928 (the 10497 number is a reference to the US catalogue number for the set, which is 497 - the number on the side of the ship remains “928” though). Sally asked me if I wanted it, and inevitably I said yes. And for Christmas 2022 Angus and I constructed it.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/10497.jpg" alt="Lego model 10497" title="Lego model 10497" />
    <figcaption>Lego model 10497 - thoughtful, sincere, huge, fragile.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>10497 is pitched as a modern version of 928, making extensive use of technic bricks for the skeleton of the ship. The standout feature is that the ship is now on two planes, with the fuselage set at a shallow angle to the wings. It looks super cool.</p>

<p>The set is about 150% of the size of the original, and features twice the number of bricks. Building it was like watching a story unfold, each element was had been chosen very thoughtfully. That said, by the end (after I estimate 10ish hours(!)) I was pretty over it. The result <em>looks</em> pretty swish - the retractable landing fear makes the orginal’s look a bit creaky. And 928’s austere cabin gets more decoration - the larger fuselage provides room for astronaut beds, the lack of which used to bother me about the old space lego ships as a kid (now, if they could just add a toilet…). There’s also an airlock door in between the cabin and the cargo area, which now pops out a ramp to get the litle car out of the ship. And the swinging rear doors are now fixed using locking pieces, a more natural solution than the 1 x 2 plate that had to be stuck on the top of the old model to keep it all in place.</p>

<p>That said, there are some downsides. The wing is now much thicker than the original - and the chunkier feel seems a bit unbalanced. Similarly the spoiler on top of the cabin now feels too large. The engines now have a more realistic look, but the old grey cones and cylinders of the original are to me the most iconic Space Lego pieces of all. But the biggest problem is that 10497 isn’t really a set to play with. Much of the exterior, esp the wing and the pieces supporting the cockpit, fall off when you touch it. The set is probably too heavy for little arms, too. Aside from the antennas, which were forever falling off, the rest of 928 was built like a brick shithouse. So not without its faults, but I’ll say that Lego did a pretty solid job with 10497.</p>

<p>Is 10497 redundant, indulgent, and pointless? Yes, but it remains a decent set, and I can’t say I regret having it.</p>

<h1 id="and-in-the-end">And in the end</h1>

<p>As with my other fixations documented here, there’s not much by way of conclusion. It’s worth giivng a shout out to <a href="http://thebrickblogger.com/2020/02/in-memory-of-lego-designer-jens-nygaard-knudsen/">Jens Nygaard Knudsen</a>, who invented not only 928 and the many of the Space Lego sets, but also the Lego minifigure. Praise him with great praise!</p>

<p>I’d like to give a “Lego isn’t what it was in the 80s” speech, but I don’t entirely believe it. It’s true that Lego from long ago feels purer than today’s swamp of sets licensed from media franchises (think Harry Potter or Star Wars), the creativity and imagination put in to Lego remains high. It’s exhausting to think of all those sets and all that plastic, but I can’t begrudge kids today having the same fun I have. So, keep going, I guess.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/lego/all.jpg" alt="Lego models 928, '929', and 10497" title="The whole gang" />
    <figcaption>The whole gang!</figcaption>
</figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is an account of my personal love affair with Lego and model LL928.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New Age of (hu)man</title><link href="/2022/08/24/new-age.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Age of (hu)man" /><published>2022-08-24T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-08-24T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/2022/08/24/new-age</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/08/24/new-age.html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to write a survey of New Age music that I like, but I’m hamstrung by not having a decent definition of what New Age music is other than <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_know_it_when_I_see_it">I know it when I hear it</a>. It’s easy to identity common elements of New Age music: trappings of Eastern mysticism, “world music” instrumentation, cosmic yearning, FM synthesisers, California; but there’s music that contains some of these elements that I struggle to think of as New Age, and music with none of these elements that I couldn’t classify as anything else.</p>

<p>I should declare my prejudice: I’m skeptical of the New Age generally. Partly this is skepticism of New Age thinking, although I confess I’m not wholly unsympathetic. Partly I find much New Age music cheesy and embarrassing. (I had a bad formative experience with Constance Demby’s Novus Magnificat as a teenager, for example.) But over the past 20 years, I’ve discovered quite a few genuinely New Age albums that are genuinely good. Some are good in spite of their New Age trappings, and some are even good because of them. It’s a strange situation, and I thought it might be interesting to explore some of this music that induces in me such conflicting feelings.</p>

<h1 id="the-harmonic-choir---hearing-solar-winds-1982">The Harmonic Choir - Hearing Solar Winds (1982)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/hearing-solar-winds.jpg" width="300" alt="Hearing Solar Winds album cover" title="Hearing Solar Winds" /></p>

<p>I first heard throat singing on KLF’s Chill Out, back in the mid 90s. My KLF-listening friends and I assumed the effect was a resonant filter put on the singer’s voice, and we only found out later that humans could actually make those sounds was pretty astonishing.</p>

<p>Overtonal singing originates from the steppe of Asia, but in the mid 1970s an American named David Hykes assembled his Harmonic Choir, to project over- and undertones to curious Western audiences.</p>

<p>Hearing Solar Winds was recorded in a French Church over several nights in 1983. It’s just voices and reverb and the occasional tinging Buddhist chime (which I find a bit unnecessary, but I don’t begrudge it).</p>

<p>Proceedings commence with Rainbow Voice, in which a solo voice emerges from the vacuum, producing, well, a spectrum of harmonics. It reminds me of the numerous hours I spent as a late teen low-pass filter sweeping a bass drone, and enjoying the hearing harmonics wink in and out of existence. This super bare arrangement - voice, harmonics, reverberation is a great platform on which to kick off the album.</p>

<p>“Multiplying Voices At the Heart of the Body of Sound” (not an early Tangerine Dream track title, but is indistinguishable from one), as the title suggests, introduces multiple voices, singing the same tone but slightly detuned to create beats. The vocal control on display is awesome, while the detuning effect gives relieves the New Agery with a bit of grit. Eventually the voices resolve into major key chords, but it doesn’t feel sappy, it feels kind of right.</p>

<p>Arc Descents - again as the title suggests, features voices slowly descending, falling out of and into tune gracefully. Spacey. The strangely modernly-titled Gravity Waves is a 2001ish soundscape of gradually evolving harmonies. The longest track is Telescoping, where the voices ranging through one another in a slowly changing, hypnotic way.</p>

<p>On Ascending and Descending the voices range up and down in a way similar to the opener Rainbow Voice. It’s slightly reminiscent of the Popul Vuh track that opens Herzog’s Nosferatu. Then the sound fades away.</p>

<p>What makes this album so good? I think part of the key is that it’s powered solely by the human voice, which makes it timeless. The voices are suspended in space too, and the church’s reverb kind leaves them floating in eternity. The motivations of the choir are New Age and the sound is warm and positive, yet none of these elements are in any way a detriment.</p>

<p>Hearing Solar Winds is a great showcase for Hykes’ vision and the Harmonic Choir’s skill. Also, the album has helped me to slumber on many a night, so thanks, team!</p>

<h1 id="steve-hillage---rainbow-dome-musick-1979">Steve Hillage - Rainbow Dome Musick (1979)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/rainbow-dome-musick.jpg" width="300" alt="Rainbow Dome Musick album cover" title="Rainbow Dome Musick" /></p>

<p>Steve Hillage and wife/partner Miquette Giraudy were previously in the prog-hippie band Gong, where the pair provided some of the group’s more contemplative electronic moments (ie tracks where no one banged on about bloody pothead pixies).</p>

<p>Rainbow Dome Musick was “Recorded for the Rainbow Dome at the Festival for Mind-Body-Spirit Olympia London April 21-29. 1979.”, which confirm’s the album’s New Age pedigree. Proceedings commence with the sound of water trickling into a pool, which, on playing back just now encouraged my wife to use the bathroom. Over this sound electric piano and synth flutter about in gently and lovingly. Gradually a spiraling sequencer comes in to play. To this celestial wafting, is added Hillage’s guitar.</p>

<p>Four Ever Rainbow starts with a ting bell sound and some raspy bass monosynth harmonic twiddling. There’s then a parade of catlike sinewaves and a plinky heavy delayed synth. It’s very New Age, but more shockingly, it sounds an awful lot like the Orb. This is no coincidence: Rainbow Dome Musick was a disc spun by the Orb’s LX Paterson and the KLF’s Jimmy Cauty when they (re)discovered ambient in the late 80s. Indeed, Hillage and Giraudy collaborated with the Orb on the wonderful Orb track Blue Room.</p>

<h1 id="iasos---inter-dimensional-music-1975">Iasos - Inter-dimensional music (1975)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/interdimensional-music.jpg" width="300" alt="Inter-dimensional Music album cover" title="Inter-dimensional Music" /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iasos_(musician)">Iasos</a> is an American-Greek New Ager, and this album from the mid 1970s feels much later than that, because it contains many New Age/ambient tropes. The music is clear and peaceful without being cloying, and there’s a fresh, bright openness to it. The arrangement is reasonably jazzy, with flute, guitar, and piano, garnished with synth washes and plenty of space in the arrangements. It’s a musical document that’s both utterly infused by the New Age, without feeling dogmatically bound to it. To me the standout track is Rainbow Canyon, which has a Gongish, Krautrocky vibe. Lots of shimmering slide or pedal-steel guitar.</p>

<h1 id="ashra---blackouts-1977">Ashra - Blackouts (1977)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/blackouts.jpg" width="300" alt="Blackouts album cover" title="Blackouts" /></p>

<p>Ashra started life as the Krautrock band Ash Ra Tempel, who produced some remarkable albums in the early 1970s (including a collaboration with Timothy Leary?!). By 1977 the group’s creative powerhouses Klaus Schulze and Manuel Gottsching had gone their own ways; Schulze had embarked on a successful solo career as a synth guru (curiously, despite his music being essentially My Thing, I’ve never been moved by it), while Gottsching rebranded as Ashra, a banner for his solo work. The title of the first Ashra album, New Age of Earth (1976), gives a clear indication of Gottsching’s intentions, but the followup album Blackouts is the one I wish to include in my “good” New Age list.</p>

<p>The first track, “77 Slightly Delayed”, is a genial piece, synth-propelled and with interest maintained by Garcia-esque guitar. (This track is in the “style” known as Berlin School, which basically boils down to a synth sequence plus a human-played solo. Initially pioneered by Tangerine Dream with their first sequencer-driven track Phaedra, the Berlin-residing artists Edgar Froese, Klaus Schulze, and Manuel Gottsching elaborated on the style through the 70s - Froese mostly on his solo albums, while Schulze and Gottsching made it their primary modus operandi.) Schulze’s Berlin School sound is (to my mind) anaemic and dull, but Gottsching gave it a bit more variation and texture, esp on his most prominent album, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E2-E4">E2-E4</a> from 1981.)</p>

<p>Track 2, Midnight on Mars, is a gentle space jazz outing. Don’t Trust The Kids, sounds more like Air than anything else!? The track is attached to its followup, Blackouts, which erupts in a blaze of guitar solo. Shuttlecock is a geometric spiral of multiple guitars and afro rhythms. Concluding the album is the more straightforwardly New Agey Lotus Part I - IV, which shuffles around reasonably cheerfully, although some dissonance is allowed in at one point.</p>

<p>New Age of Earth is more straightforwardly New Age than Blackouts, but because of that it’s less interesting. Is Blackouts New Age enough? Well, if you compare it to the primordial fire of Ash Ra Tempel’s first album, it is, yes. If you compare it to something <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hearts_of_Space_Records">Hearts of Spacey</a>, not so much. Interestingly, the Ashra album following Blackouts, Correlations (1979), was a more rock(!) affair, so it’s almost like over the course of three albums Gottsching recanted his New Age swerve.</p>

<p>Blackouts then, represents an imperfect example of the Krautrock trend of evolving from experimental rock to a much softer, more appealing and largely New Age sound. Tangerine Dream, Michael Rother, Popul Vuh (earlier than most), and Cluster (on increasingly New Age label Sky Records!) all went there. Those that didn’t faded into obscurity, or were Kraftwerk. It was a strangely weak end to arguably the most fertile art music movement in the late 20th Century. On the other hand, if it paid for mortgages, you know, fair enough.</p>

<h1 id="tony-scott---music-for-zen-meditation-and-other-joys-1964">Tony Scott - Music for Zen Meditation and Other Joys (1964)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/music-for-zen-meditation.jpg" width="300" alt="Music for Zen Meditation album cover" title="Music for Zen Meditation" /></p>

<p>Tony Scott was primarily a jazz clarinetist, but was interested in music from other cultures, and produced an album sufficiently early to be considered the first of the New Age. (You could make a case for it being a seminal ambient or world music album too. Hell, let’s add jazz fusion to the list just for fun.)</p>

<p>The arrangement is very minimal: Scott &amp; clarinet, plus koto and shakuhachi. At first the music sounds like standard minor key Japanese folk music, but Scott’s clarinet puts in enough bend to the notes that you realise you’re listening to something deliberately other. Scott isn’t merely - and I’m putting this perhaps too crudely - “going native”, he’s contributing his own ideas to Japanese music.</p>

<p>There’s another joy to the album: being the first album of World or New Age music, it’s completely unselfconscious. Clearly, purely New Age, without any of the bullshit that the genre later accreted.</p>

<p>My only criticism of Music for Zen Meditation - and a more general criticism of this mode of Japanese folk music - is that the minimal arrangement, the meditative mood, and the traditional scale used make for a very limited style. I know that that’s kind of the point: the intent is to transport the listener’s mind to the same Zen place, every Zen time; but I think it’s still worth pointing out. You could listen to one song or 100 albums, you’re only going to get only one effect.</p>

<h1 id="michael-stearns---planetary-unfolding-1981">Michael Stearns - Planetary Unfolding (1981)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/planetary-unfolding.jpg" width="300" alt="Planetary Unfolding album cover" title="Planetary Unfolding" /></p>

<p>Michael Stearns’ biggest claim to fame is that he scored the early 90s “non-narrative” (apparently) documentary film Baraka. His career began a long way before that, however, and Planetary Unfolding is a remarkable document from the early 80s. The first track, “In the Beginning”, unfurls inexorably from a quiet bass drone into a transcendent crescendo that I would have to say is the transcendiest and cresciendiest that I’ve ever heard.</p>

<p>The rest of the album proceeds with much the same majesty. The only duff track is Life in the Gravity Well, but even then because it contains a wailing chanteuse part that isn’t to my taste. (Now I’m not against wailing in itself: there’s a similar example in the KLF’s Chill Out, and I am completely in awe of Ofra Haza. No, it’s the particular <em>style</em> of this wailing: it’s a New Age, swims-with-dolphins and gives-birth-underwater kind of a wail. That’s how I think about it, anyway.)</p>

<p>The final track, Something’s Moving, starts with a tickyticky sound that is quite odd for a concluding track, but it music eventually resolves with a wonderful sense of completion.</p>

<p>On the face of it there’s not much about Plantary Unfolding is definitively New Age; it could be considered space rock, or ambient. For me the New Ageyness is in the unashamed embrace of grandeur and transcendence. It’s not something Eno would find tasteful; Tangerine Dream would embrace it but also make it cold and alien. Another element crucial to the album’s success is the use of early 80s analog-synthesis-in-its-prime synths, rather than mid 80s digital synths, which would have given the album a more brittle sound (see Novus Magnificat).</p>

<p>A further revelation is that the album as a whole reminds me of my favourite ambient album, the KLF’s Chill Out. This could be put down to the superficial similarity of the synthetic arrangements, but I suspect that somewhere deep down there is a kindred spirit between Rockman, King Boy, and New Age practitioners like Stearns. (Come to think of it, I’ve just remembered the KLF’s obsession with Ley Lines. And Jimmy Cauty did those posters for Lord of the Rings. But worryingly, if there’s a bit of New Age even in pop’s most piss-taking pranksters, then really no one’s safe.)</p>

<h1 id="enya---watermark-1988">Enya - Watermark (1988)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/watermark.jpg" width="300" alt="Watermark album cover" title="Watermark" /></p>

<p>Despite my disgust at Constance Demby (poor old Constance, RIP), 15 year old me did very much enjoy the fiddle-dee-dee Celtic stylings of Enya (and for that matter, her family’s work on Clannad’s Robin of Sherwood soundtrack a few years earlier). Genre check: is Enya actually New Age, or merely Irish? Well, I’m confident many babies have been birthed (in the light of numerous scented candles) to her soothing, multitracked warbles, so I’m going to say yes.</p>

<p>Is Watermark actually good? Yeah, I reckon. Why not? Can I declare here and now my love for Orinoco Flow? Oh, go on then.</p>

<h1 id="james-holden---the-animal-spirits-2017">James Holden - The Animal Spirits (2017)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/the-animal-spirits.jpg" width="300" alt="The Animal Spirits album cover" title="The Animal Spirits" /></p>

<p>James Holden has a storied pedigree as a DJ and remixer with a sideline producing wonky electronica using modular synth(s?). Holden’s album The Animal Spirits was recorded with a band. The result sometimes sounds a bit like Terry Riley, and sometimes it recalls a 1970s psychedelia-infused tribal jazz. The result is really great.</p>

<p>Without knowing more about motivations of Holden and his cadre, I can’t say if The Animal Spirits was intended to be New Age, but I detect a strong sense of English paganism in the music. It’s not necessarily a paganism from the past; it could equally be a paganism of a post-civilisation come-down. Or chalk horses, maybe. Even if the intent and effect is of a different kind to crystals’n’chakras New Age, it still feels like there’s <em>something</em> New Agey there. It’s not just me, right?</p>

<h1 id="popul-vuh---hosianna-mantra-1972">Popul Vuh - Hosianna Mantra (1972)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/new-age/hosianna-mantra.jpg" width="300" alt="Hosianna Mantra album cover" title="Hosianna Mantra" /></p>

<p>After two albums of Moog doodlings (one average, one pretty good), Popul Vuh’s leader Florian Fricke decided to ditch the electronics and form a band. The concept for Hosianna Mantra was to fuse Eastern and Western religious musical styles. That sounds like a recipe for disaster, but it was the early 70s and Fricke was a Krautrocker, so the result was always going to be more interesting than would appear on paper.</p>

<p>The key to the album’s success is the earnest simplicity of the music. Fricke took maximal advantage of his eclectic arrangement (piano, oboe, guitar, sitar, and - most crucially - the tender, classically-trained voice of Djong Yun). The album is very much of its time, and might be considered naive to modern ears, but I can’t help but admire it as being highly singular and wholly original.</p>

<h1 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h1>

<p>So there you have it: a bunch of different musics from different times, from musicians with different motivations and backgrounds. We can say then that music that at least I consider to be New Age is not all bad, and I’ve discovered that if you’re creative enough you can transcend the constraints of any genre. Should I have known that already? Probably, yes. But the lesson has been learned, at least for this musical style. Next stop: Christian dubstep!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I want to write a survey of New Age music that I like, but I’m hamstrung by not having a decent definition of what New Age music is other than I know it when I hear it. It’s easy to identity common elements of New Age music: trappings of Eastern mysticism, “world music” instrumentation, cosmic yearning, FM synthesisers, California; but there’s music that contains some of these elements that I struggle to think of as New Age, and music with none of these elements that I couldn’t classify as anything else.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jarre-ing experiences</title><link href="/2022/06/19/jmj.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jarre-ing experiences" /><published>2022-06-19T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-06-19T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/2022/06/19/jmj</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/06/19/jmj.html"><![CDATA[<p>Growing up in the early 80s I was aware of synthesized sound. I don’t know why I found the bloops interesting - perhaps it was the common presence of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kVvdFRtBnMA&amp;t=137s">“synthetic electronic sound”</a> in science fiction TV shows that made it so evocative to me. Older people seemed to find electronic sounds cold and alienating, but for me they were beguiling.</p>

<p>Though I was aware of the early 80s synth pop boom to some degree (I certainly remember when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_You_Want_Me">Don’t You Want Me</a> (1981) came out, and when <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_Monday_(New_Order_song)">Blue Monday</a> (1983) played in the background at the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coronation_Street">Rover’s Return</a>), I was more focused on electronic musical cues from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctor_Who">Doctor Who</a>, or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buck_Rogers_in_the_25th_Century_(TV_series)">Buck Rogers in the 25th Century</a>, or indeed from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vangelis">Vangelis</a>’ ubiquitous 1981 synth hit <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8a-HfNE3EIo">Chariots of Fire</a>. (I was especially impressed by how Vangelis’ studio setup had him besieged by keyboards.) But more than any of these things, the music I remember most being fascinated was this anonymous but vivid electronica that got played whenever our local television transmitter lost its upstream feed (something that happened at that time more often than you’d think). This anonymous soundtrack featured a blaze of electronic sound which I found captivating and mysterious at the age of I dunno, somewhere between 6 and 8.</p>

<p>I don’t want to over-emphasise my interest in sound - children are fleetingly interested in lots of things. But there was something about it that persisted over time, even if in a minor way compared to say <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cricket">cricket</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asterix">Asterix</a>. I really dug the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Art_of_Noise">Art of Noise’s</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-sFK0-lcjGU">Close to the Edit</a> (1984), and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Hardcastle">Paul Hardcastle</a>’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0sajngb0W6I">Nineteen</a> (1985). (I wasn’t quite so taken by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yello">Yello</a>’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oh_Yeah_(Yello_song)">Oh Yeah</a> though.) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pump_Up_the_Volume_(song)">Pump up the Volume</a> (1987) was a revelation (though possibly more for the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w9gOQgfPW4Y">royalty free Nasa footage used in the video</a> than its pioneering house-in-the-charts sound).</p>

<p>In any event, it seems I was primed in some way when, in 1990, I saw an ad on TV for <a href="https://www.discogs.com/release/11210949-Ed-Starink-Synthesizer-Greatest">Synthesiser Greatest</a> (volume 1), a collection of synth hits distributed in my homeland by the cheap and cheerful <a href="https://www.discogs.com/label/198393-Dino-Music-Pty-Limited">Dino Records</a>. The ad featured a tune I recognised from the TV transmitter breakdown music. I had never bought music before, but I was sufficiently moved to buy this compilation. And so it was, on my 15th birthday, I acquired Synthesizer Greatest on cassette.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/synthesizer-greatest.jpg" width="600" alt="Synthesizer Greatest album cover" title="Synthesizer Greatest album cover" /></p>

<p>The album, as I discovered later, featured covers only (boo!) by a Dutchman going by the name <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ed_Starink">Ed Starink</a>. (I thought this name was an embarrassing pseudonym, but apparently it isn’t?!) The vibe of the enterprise was pretty cheap and cheesy, and I wouldn’t say it was the sort of thing I’d buy now (or even a year after I bought it). But to be fair the quality of the covers was actually pretty solid, and the tracklist gave me plenty of points for further investigation:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Autobahn (Kraftwerk)</li>
  <li>Moments in Love (Art of Noise)</li>
  <li>Electricity (OMD)</li>
  <li>Pulstar (Vangelis)</li>
  <li>Oxygene part IV (Jarre)</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/synthesizer-greatest-cassette.jpg" alt="Synthesizer Greatest cassette tape" title="This is what a tape looked like, kids" /></p>

<p>Oxygene IV was the track I recognised from the ad, and its composer now had a name: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Michel_Jarre">Jean Michel Jarre</a>. The hunt was on! Over the next couple of years I obtained (new, second hand, or <em>cough</em> dubbed onto tape) ten Jarre albums. This post contains reflections on what I found.</p>

<p>Let’s give it up for Synthesizer Greatest. <em>clap</em> <em>clap</em> <em>clap</em></p>

<h2 id="digression-now-thats-what-i-call-not-now-music">Digression: Now that’s what I call not-now music</h2>

<p>Before we get to the subject at hand, it’s worth pausing to wonder why I was off on this hunt for out-of-date music rather than digging through white label vinyl at the freshest record shop in town? Or to put another way, why the idiosyncratic exploration of sounds I’d heard 10 years earlier? Well, part of the answer is I wasn’t really aware of the contemporary electronic scene at the time. My immediate social circle was obsessed with goth and indie rock, of nearly the same vintage of Jarre’s heyday. Others were listening to Led Zeppelin with the same fervour as Nirvana… In any event I didn’t really interact with contemporary electronica until I reached university.</p>

<p>More generally though, I’ve seldom listened to contemporary music. I tend to be a bit sceptical of novelty until it’s had a chance to percolate. I guess that speaks to an inherent conservatism on my part, and well, yes…</p>

<p>Now, I’ve got that off my chest, let’s explore the disocgraphy of Jean Michel Jarre.</p>

<h1 id="oxygene-1976">Oxygene (1976)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/oxygene.jpg" width="300" alt="Oxygene album cover" title="Oxygene album cover" /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oxyg%C3%A8ne">Oxygene</a> wasn’t the first Jarre album I heard, but it makes more sense to start with this album.</p>

<p>My Oxygene year zero was in August 1991. After listening to the Jarre tracks on Synthesizer Greatest, Oxygene became a sort of holy grail for me. Buying it was a bit of a punt because it cost NZ$19.95, which wasn’t that much money then, but on my budget was a fair bit, which could have been spent on two classical cassettes. Would the benefit justify the cost?!</p>

<p>I still get misty eyed remembering it. It was a sunny Wednesday and I caught the lunch time train from school into town for an orthodontist’s appointment, and delayed my return to education by a few minutes to quickly duck into the nearest music shop (of which there were many back then) and buy Oxygene. Braces tightened, teeth hurting, I executed my musical purchase and sprinted back to the station in time for the next train. Once safely onboard, I placed the tape into my mid-price Walkman (no Dolby B noise reduction, but it did have a three band equaliser), and listened through the first side on the train back to school. I remember listening and feeling a sense of relief that I was enjoying it; more than that even, I found the music transcendant. Unfortunately school got in the way of listening all the way through; the second side had to wait until I got home. When I finally had a chance to listen, the experience was just as pleasurable. Jarre got a fan for life that day.</p>

<p>Oxygene part 1 starts with a genial cyclical burble of synths through echoes. Proceedings move around in a plinketty plonketty way. Eventually the fizz evaporates and there’s a subdued, eerie theme. Toward the end the plink-plonks resume to facilitate a more dramatic transition into Part II. Overall part I is a fairly straightforward mood piece, but it sets the scene well.</p>

<p>Part II commences with a series of repeating sequences building up to a crescendo of urgency, before commencing a dramatic melody, punctuated by sine wobbles from a VCS3. This was another theme I remember from TV transmitter breakdown interludes. After the first melody, the track shifts into another theme, which thunders away emphatically with a bit of noodly soloing, until the track fades away into a slow up-and-down sweep of white noise through a <a href="https://www.tonepedia.com/catalog/effects-and-pedals/chorus-and-vibrato/small-stone-v1-1975/">Small Stone phaser</a> (if there was a Nobel Prize for use of audio effects, Jarre deserved one for Services to Phasing on Oxygene and Equinoxe). Part III is a more sedate almost oriental-sounding piece, which ends with a field recording of birdsong. This brings side 1 to a serene conclusion.</p>

<p>Oxygene part IV I already knew from Synthesizer Greatest. I learned a lot later that the Jarre just slowed down <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hot_Butter">Hot Butter</a>’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YK3ZP6frAMc">Popcorn</a>, and - hey presto - futuristic synth majesty. Oxygene V started with what feels almost church music, a slightly ponderous progression of chords, replaced with the same theme sped up, with a bit of moog brassy soloing that sounds reminiscent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurice_Ravel">Ravel</a>’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bol%C3%A9ro">Bolero</a>. Finally part VI is a track whose arrangement screams “cheesy French <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lounge_music">lounge music</a>”, but is played minor-key straight. It’s a very open and ambiguous conclusion to proceedings, which is exactly what the album needs.</p>

<h2 id="waxing-lyrical">Waxing lyrical</h2>

<p>Where to start praising Oxygene? Well, to begin somewhere, the album made a huge impression on 16 year old me. The sound was just so vivid, and spoke to me of a crepuscular world of stone, sky, wood, and water, but devoid of people. It’s the sound of the planet before humans evolved, or the planet that will exist after we’re gone. To continue the pseudo-poetic vein, it’s the sound you’d hear if you could only strip away the overlying noise of human <em>fuss</em>.</p>

<p>Flowery phrasery aside, the genius of Oxygene is that its parts are carefully constructed to enhance each other. Consider the flow of the tracks:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Part I is a great introduction</li>
  <li>Part II ups the ante</li>
  <li>Part III provides good contrast and concludes side A perfectly.</li>
  <li>Part IV restarts proceedings dramatically, and is the stand out track (and single)</li>
  <li>Part V begins as a languid change of pace, before stepping up a gear and providing a bit of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arcadia_(utopia)">arcadian</a> longing</li>
  <li>Part VI provides a muted “come-down” to conclude the album.</li>
</ul>

<p>Not only do the moods in this sequence contrast and balance nicely, the continuous mix (aside from the gap between side 1 and 2) seamlessly blends one track into another, making the album feel like a journey.</p>

<p>The sound is incredibly crisp and precise, and clear - despite being <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/music/2018/oct/16/jean-michel-jarre-michel-granger-oxygene">recorded in Jarre’s kitchen</a> rather than in a professional studio. The relative gain levels between the instruments are expertly balanced both in gain and stereo space. Finally, as icing on the cake, there’s Jarre’s winning choice of <a href="http://www.granger-michel.com/project/oxygene-1972/">Michel Granger’s surreal painting</a> for the album cover.</p>

<p>Now I’ll concede that without the nostalgic reference points baked into my head, a contemporary Oxygene listener might not see it as an electronica album for the ages. (They be wondering “where’s the kick drum?”) But for what it’s worth, I reckon Oxygene transcends its era. As a document of 70s electronica at Oxygene is perhaps the most quintessential.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jmj/oxygene-back-cover.jpg" width="600" alt="Oxygene album back cover" title="Oxygene album back cover" />
    <figcaption>Oxygene back cover. Oui, oui, d'accord</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="prehistory">Prehistory</h2>

<p>Before we go further, it’s worth pointing out that prior to Oxygene, Jarre had released two previous albums, both in 1973. One was a set of stock music, the other a film soundtrack.</p>

<p>I didn’t get to hear them until the 2010s. I can report they’re pretty average - standard electronic fare for the time, and not compelling enough for a second listen. Yet, in a way, this only serves to make Oxygene more impressive. I’m curious to know what changed in Jarre’s compositional outlook between <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Granges_Br%C3%BBl%C3%A9es_(album)">Les Granges Brûlées</a> in 1973, and Oxygene three years later. Was Oxygene as intentional as it seems listening to it now, or was the result more of a happy accident, where the six tracks just happened to work together so well?</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-video">Embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kSIMVnPA994" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>He began as he meant to go on.</p>

<h1 id="equinoxe-1978">Equinoxe (1978)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/equinoxe.jpg" width="300" alt="Equinoxe album cover" title="Equinoxe album cover" /></p>

<p>Since Oxygene had proven an excellent purchase, I resolved to buy Jarre’s followup, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%89quinoxe">Equinoxe</a>. I obtained it the afternoon before I went up country on a trip with my history class. While coach loudspeakers blared out Bob Marley, I cranked up my <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walkman">Walkman</a> and witnessed Equinoxe for the first time. (Incidentally I’ve held a grudge against Marley fans and boycotted his music ever since - even though I realise it’s hardly his fault. But I’m sure you’ll agree that things that happen at high school really stay with you.)</p>

<p>Equinoxe Part I is a major key fanfare by way of frenzied arpeggiation. It is a more confident, emphatic, and bombastic start to an album than Oxygene’s part I. Part II, by contrast, is haunted phased soundscape. Part III kicks off as a rather lovely waltz, which soon decays into a some sonic brooding and bubbling. Part IV was the album’s most exciting discovery for me - in the early 80s it was used as the title music for a long-running nature documentary series in my country in the early 1980s. Equinoxe was the highlight of my trip - well, that and getting a chance to have a chat with a girl I fancied (I used the opportunity to boast about how much weetbix I could eat. I’ll concede that as romantic openings go, it was absolutely dire.)</p>

<p>Side two begins with Part V, which I’d heard before on Synthesizer Greatest. It’s very much The Single, jaunty and cheerful, directing us towards our Glorious Utopian Future. It’s decent, but doesn’t quite have the resonance of Oxygene IV, though. Part VI keeps up Part V’s tempo, and is really charming in a sample-hold, techno futuristic way.</p>

<p>Part VII starts off with a nice piece of bass work, but develops into an lengthy and slightly underdeveloped workout that doesn’t quite justify its length. Eventually the rhythm, which hasn’t relented since Part V began, eases away. Part VIII starts out with a rendering of synthetic oompah band playing in a thunderstorm - quirky choice, that - before recapitulating Part V’s theme in a churchy kind of way. The conclusion is a kind of uplifting Amen.</p>

<p>Up to part VII Equinoxe was on par in terms of quality to Oxygene; the only detracting point would be that the album cleaves very closely to Oxygene’s template. (That doesn’t particularly bother me; not every album has to be a significant development on the last.) Unfortunately, however, parts VII and VIII, don’t quite see the album out with the same emphaticness that parts V and VI of Oxygene do. It’s not enough to derail the whole work, but it is a shame Jarre ran out of inspiration on the home strait.</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-video-1">Embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/MO7--KBgpAQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Nice cravat.</p>

<h1 id="magnetic-fields-1981">Magnetic Fields (1981)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/magnetic-fields.jpg" width="300" alt="Magnetic fields album cover" title="Magnetic fields album cover" /></p>

<p>Magnetic Fields finds Jarre at something of a crossroads. Equinoxe had been a play-it-safe sequel to Oxygene, but by 1981 the electronic music landscape had changed a lot since 1976. Understandably, for his next album, Jarre looked to innovate by obtaining a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fairlight_CMI">Fairlight CMI</a>, a fabulously expensive and very much way-of-the-future digital sampler.</p>

<p>Unfortunately the Fairlight only recognisably appears in one or two places on the album (it would be used far more authoritatively on Jarre’s next disc). Instead, the album largely relies on analogue synthesisers.</p>

<p>The first side of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Chants_Magn%C3%A9tiques">Magnetic Fields</a> is taken up by Magnetic Fields part I. In truth Part I is actually three tracks: an initial urgent introduction that gives an impression of relentless motion. Then there’s an interlude of floating music concrete, followed by another minor key romp to the piece’s conclusion. The overall impression I had from first listen is that it just isn’t engaging as the first sides of Oxygene or Equinoxe.</p>

<p>Side two begins (as usual) with a single, the rambunctious Magnetic Fields part II. The track is the first Jarre number to feature percussion up loud in the mix. It’s not a bad track, but it lacks the majestic transcendance of Oxygene IV, or the cheery utopia of Equinoxe part V. Worryingly for Jarre, the version on Synthesizer Greatest is actually better (thumbs up to Ed Starink!).</p>

<p>For me the best track on the album is Magnetic Fields part III. It’s a relatively straightforward mix of spiralling arpeggios, water sploshing, synthetic bass and what could be a slowed thumb piano loop. To me it’s the only track on the album that has any room to breathe.</p>

<p>Part IV is a sort of limp anthem that plods away for a while, modulates into minor key for a further while, and kind of slinks away with a field recording of a train. A bit like Equinoxe part VII it’s not bad, but just not that interesting.</p>

<p>If Part IV is lacklustre, part V (named on a later Jarre compilation as “The Last Rumba”) is, like Oxygene Part VI a lounge music excursion. But while its predecessor has a contemplative, even melancholic tone, The Last Rumba is profoundly cheesy, and doesn’t bear repeated listening.</p>

<p>Magnetic Fields for me is Jarre’s difficult third album. Jarre clearly wanted to move into new territory with Magnetic Fields, but the result was a bit crap. If you want to look at genuinely innovative 1981 electronic albums, consider Kraftwerk’s Computerworld, where they basically invented techno. By contrast, the lumpy style of Magnetic Fields
didn’t lead to anything.</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-video-2">Embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w434qhNJMdw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Embarrassing, yes, but an improvement on before.</p>

<h1 id="zoolook-1984">Zoolook (1984)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/zoolook.jpg" width="300" alt="Zoolook album cover" title="Zoolook album cover" /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zoolook">Zoolook</a> was the first Jarre album I listened to, obtaining it on CD from my local library in early 1991. It’s perhaps not the most appropriate introduction to Jarre’s music, but in a way that makes it a more interesting starting point. I remember sticking the CD into the player, donning some ridiculously large 70s headphones and almost immediately hearing sounds I’d never heard before.</p>

<p>For Zoolook Jarre had another crack reinventing his sound, and features collaborations with musicians as unexpected as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laurie_Anderson">Laurie Anderson</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adrian_Belew">Adrian Belew</a>. The Fairlight CMI, used somewhat timidly in Magnetic Fields, was front and centre on Zoolook. (Apparently the first version of the Fairlight didn’t have a sequencer, and this may account for its limited use on the earlier album, and greater prominence here.) Also in contrast to earlier albums, the primary musical medium of Zoolook is the human voice, sampled and processed.</p>

<p>The first track, Ethnicolor, is a psychedelic, Vangelistic (Vangelisian?) excursion quite unlike anything Jarre had produced before. The clarity of makes a welcome return, the digital technology providing a crisper frequency response than Magnetic Fields’ wall of arpeggiating synths. The sound is greatly modernised, with live drums filtered through gated reverb in a typically mid 80s style. Slap bass even makes an appearance, as welcome as it is surprising. The only downside to the track is that the early melody is played through a vocal sample that sounds like “tit”.</p>

<p>The next track, Diva, featuring Laurie Anderson on vocals, begins with a languorous introduction, followed by a more frenetic workout propped up by african-style drumming and guitar. That’s not a description that sounds promising, but it really works.</p>

<p>There follows the title track, which is a piece of excellent synth funk(!), slightly reminiscent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Hancock">Herbie Hancock</a>’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rockit_(instrumental)">Rockit</a> (esp the music video), but also sufficiently its own thing not to excite Hancock’s lawyers.</p>

<p>Then there’s the spooky dreamtime evocation of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woolloomooloo">Woolloomooloo</a>. I actually think it’s one of Jarre’s best tracks. Just so well realised.</p>

<p>After that comes Zoolookologie, a fizzing pop track which zings away happily, its only blemish being a recapitulation of that distracting “tit” sample from Ethnicolor.</p>

<p>Heading into the home straight, there’s Blah Blah Cafe, a stomping piece of silliness, that has a similar function to The Last Rumba on Magnetic Fields, only it isn’t fucking terrible.</p>

<p>The final track is the grave, contemplative Ethnicolor II, which is the perfect sendoff for the album.</p>

<p>Zoolook is - to me at least - Jarre’s second best album after Oxygene. What I admire most about it is that Jarre completely reinvented his sound and approach, and it completely pays off.</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-videos">Embarrassing music videos</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-F36bJ57TmM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>This is actually not too bad, so as a bonus, here’s one that’s much worse:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iIeAt5invw0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>DID YOU KNOW THIS WAS MADE IN THE 1980s?</p>

<h1 id="rendez-vous-1986">Rendez-Vous (1986)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/rendez-vous.jpg" width="300" alt="Rendez-Vous album cover" title="Rendez-Vous album cover" /></p>

<p>With Zoolook marking a much-needed fresh start to Jarre’s career, his next album capitalised on this by creating a remarkable fusion of jazz and ambient electronica which both looked back to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miles_Davis">Miles Davis</a>’ <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_a_silent_way">In a Silent Way</a>, and forward to the 90s Ambient movement.</p>

<p>Well, that’s the album I’d like for him to have made. But he didn’t. In fact, what happened next was pretty dire.</p>

<h2 id="houston-calling">Houston calling</h2>

<p>Rendez-Vous has a bit of a backstory you need to understand before we can discuss it, so settle in. It all started when Jarre was invited to perform in Houston for a celebration of 25 years of Nasa and 150 years of Texas. The performance was to be played in front of a massive audience, with a light show beamed across skyscrapers in the centre of Houston.</p>

<p>This scenario might seem a bit random, but that’s because I’ve neglected to mention Jarre’s concert exploits. On Bastille Day 1979 he performed in Paris to an audience of 1 million, putting him into the Guinness Book of Records. In 1981 he gave a series of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Les_Concerts_en_Chine">concerts in China</a>, these being the first western performances in China since the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cultural_Revolution">Cultural Revolution</a>. These experiences made Jarre somewhat credible as a booking for the Houston concert. Perhaps Houston natives <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ZZ_Top">ZZ Top</a> would have been a more appropriate choice, but Jarre got the invitation anyway.</p>

<p>For the concert, called Rendez-Vous Houston, Jarre went all-in, producing a new album (called Rendez-Vous, naturally) to release on the same day as the performance (you need to capitalise on these opportunities, right?). He also worked with astronaut and saxonphonist Ron McNair to prepare a piece McNair would record while in orbit on the space shuttle. Preparations went well until McNair died in the Challenger disaster in January 1986. A disconsolate Jarre wanted to pull the plug on the project, but was persuaded to continue. Even so, the concert was plagued with problems ahead of the performance. The concert happened, despite the fire brigade taking an understandably jaundiced view of fireworks ash raining down on the crowd. In the end Jarre was able to advance his personal concert attendance record from 1 to 1.3 million people.</p>

<h2 id="a-digression-on-authenticity-in-jarres-live-performances">A digression on authenticity in Jarre’s live performances</h2>

<p>Jarre’s early live performances were a bit cagey because, while there were some live elements - notably percussion - much of the music was lifted from his studio albums. Now there is some practical necessity in this in that it was very difficult to replicate a multitrack recording live, esp with the limitations of 80s synth hardware. So I could give it a pass on the basis that the performance was a blend of backing track and some live sound. (For an example of this done right, see <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=z8TXjhWCQPE">Depeche Mode’s 101 concert</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/s4199VMeeQc?t=389">Fletch’s uncertain contributions</a> not withstanding.)</p>

<p>When I turned 17 I shelled out for a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GYio7l7B940">VHS tape of Jarre’s Houston performance</a>. Now it may be a function of the video edit but what Jarre appeared to be doing on stage had no correlation to the music, leaving me wondering if Jarre was merely pretending. To be fair, the vid does suggest Jarre’s semi-circular keyboard controlled the lighting in some way, but that also seems a bit of a cop out.</p>

<p>I’m not alone in this view. The normally genial UK comedian <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bill_Bailey">Bill Bailey</a> was moved to declare that “Jean Michel Jarre is a fraud”. Listening to the FM broadcast of the concert rather confirms Bailey’s allegations. To my ear, much of the music is tracks lifted verbatim from Jarre’s earlier albums.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qhMXqeygBcA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>So, open and shut case for fraud? At face value, yes. But taking a step back we can wonder about the practicality of doing an actual one-off performance with the instrumentation needed to replicate Jarre’s back catalogue with sufficient fidelity to feel “full-strength”, and live. One of the drawbacks of the Concert in China album is that while it feels more live, the sound is less fleshed out, and that’s even with the overdubs Jarre felt compelled to add to the performance. This may have influenced decisions made for Rendez-Vous Houston.</p>

<p>There are other factors. Unlike the Concerts in China, Rendez-Vous Houston was a one off, so there was less incentive to be live for a single concert than there would be for multi-date tour. Jarre may also have simply not had the time or budget to organise a genuinely live performance. And finally, the reality of the Houston concert is that it was primarily about spectable, and music was very much secondary to the light show. Having an accompanying concert might have been important, but for an average punter, how the sound got generated was probably of little to no interest.</p>

<p>So Jarre’s view could well be summed up as “there will be sound, and we will satisfy the conventions of a concert in having at least some of that sound played live”. Is it cynical of Jarre? I don’t actually know. If you went to a Led Zep concert and Led Zeppelin didn’t actually play, you’d be rightly outraged, since Led Zep were a collection of rock gods, and if they were there there’s no excuse for them not to play. If you go to a light show with music played by this guy you don’t know called Jean Michel Jarre who does all this complicated stuff with electronic sound, if 75% of the sound is pre-recorded, well, is that really an ethical travesty?</p>

<p>So it’s hard to say that Jarre didn’t deliver the goods at Rendez-Vous Houston. But when 17 year old me realised that Jarre was just pretending in the Rendez-Vous concert, I found myself profoundly disappointed with him. Because if you’re not actually playing, why be on stage pretending?</p>

<h2 id="rendezvous-with-rendez-vous">Rendezvous with Rendez-Vous</h2>

<p>Rendez-Vous the album is a slight nod to the past (coming ten years after the release of Oxygene, it uses a new Michel Grainger painting on its cover, and features 6 tracks like Oxygene). But unlike the later Oxygene 7-13 album, the music and tone is unrelated. Instead, Rendez-Vous takes in a new stylistic departure: bombast. Now ok, there had been slightly operatic moments of drama in Jarre’s earlier work, most notably on Zoolook, but Rendez-Vous goes truly over the top, and not in a good way. But the most egregious horror is the saccharine Fourth Rendez-Vous. I’d heard this all the way back on Synthesizer Greatest and thought it a bit trite (or as trite as a 15 year old can find anything), but embedded in its parent album, it’s just the worst.</p>

<p>The only track I find reasonably decent is the closer, Final Rendez-Vous. This is the track that was to feature McNair’s saxophone. In his honour the track is subtitled Ron’s Theme. It’s an effective track, if more melodramatic than I prefer.</p>

<p>Elsewhere, it’s slim pickings. Compared to the lush arrangement of Zoolook, the sound in Rendez-Vous is stripped back, and more synth-oriented than Zoolook. The album feels a bit underproduced, too.</p>

<p>Why is Rendez-vous so bad? And why did Jarre turn his back on the creatively rich sound world of Zoolook? There’s so many possible reasons: perhaps Zoolook was costly to produce, didn’t sell as well as previous albums, and Jarre felt obliged to make his next album more commercial. Perhaps he was simply pushed for time producing Rendez-Vous for the concert, and cut a few corners with the arrangement. Regardless of what I might speculate, the album sold 3 million copies and - lamentably - set the tone for Jarre’s next album, Revolutions.</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-video-3">Embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vCLEZM_N0K8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>So bad.</p>

<h1 id="revolutions-1988">Revolutions (1988)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/revolutions.jpg" width="300" alt="Revolutions album cover" title="Revolutions album cover" /></p>

<p>Revolutions is a kind of retread of Rendez-Vous, this time focusing on various social, political, and technological revolutions. Thematically this seems like a rich starting point, and the album certainly tries to cover a lot of ground. The sound is a bit more developed, this time, with arguably the best percussion patterns of Jarre’s career.</p>

<p>So that’s all good. But the bombast is still prevalent, and there’s clearly an eye to another concert (this time the comparatively under-attended Destination Docklands in London in 1988).</p>

<p>While Revolutions is largerly dire, there is one unreservedly decent track: the uneasy and saxy Tokyo Kid. In keeping with the Japanese theme, I think this piece would be quite at home on the soundtrack of a dystopian anime like Akira or Ghost in the Shell - high praise, but justified, I think. So good work on that one at least, Jean Michel.</p>

<p>But the rest of the album… ugh. The nadir is September, a tribute to an ANC activist assassinated in Paris in 1988. The tribute idea is of course perfectly decent, but the tune is so sugary it’s impossible to take. Furthermore there’s a singer belting out a gospel solo in the manner of Clare Torry on Pink Floyd’s The Great Gig in the Sky. This is one instance where Jarre’s “borrowing” doesn’t lead to a decent result.</p>

<h2 id="embarrassing-music-video-4">Embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w94lmvHoUNQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Ugh.</p>

<h1 id="waiting-for-cousteau-1991">Waiting for Cousteau (1991)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/waiting-for-cousteau.jpg" width="300" alt="Waiting for cousteau album cover" title="Waiting for cousteau album cover" /></p>

<p>An album in tribute to scuba-diving mariner Jacques Cousteau, side one features something no one asked for: Jarre’s take on Calypso music (quelle horreur!). Side 2 features the long, ambient title track, which is pretty decent, if derivative of Brian Eno’s dreary Thursday Afternoon-style ambience.</p>

<h2 id="not-embarrassing-music-video">Not embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tLulE8_KAZc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Music’s not great, but give it up to the animators!</p>

<h1 id="chronologie-1993">Chronologie (1993)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/chronologie.jpg" width="300" alt="Chronologie album cover" title="Chronologie album cover" /></p>

<p>Chronologie (a concept album about Stephen Hawking’s A Brief History of time, apparently) is better, but nowhere near Jarre’s best. There’s a few half-hearted nods to contemporary electronic dance, but otherwise it’s all business-as-usual.</p>

<p>I have fonder feelings towards this album than perhaps I should, because I bought it while on a highly enjoyable holiday in Australia.</p>

<h2 id="embarassing-music-video">Embarassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Eqilin4Cv08" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>More boring than embarrassing, really, save for the moment where Jarre spins around to face the camera in a manner reminiscent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garth_Marenghi%27s_Darkplace">Garth Marenghi</a>.</p>

<h1 id="oxygene-7-13-1997">Oxygene 7-13 (1997)</h1>

<p><img src="/assets/jmj/oxygene-7-13.jpg" width="300" alt="Oxygene 7-13 album cover" title="Oxygene 7-13 album cover" /></p>

<p>Jarre didn’t release any new material for four years and I largely moved on from him. But when I discovered Oxygene 7-13 existed, I was sufficiently curious to obtain the album.</p>

<p>Brought out for the 20th anniversary of Oxygene, the new instalment was a return to that sound world, with Jarre utilising (mostly) the same synthesizers.</p>

<p>The first track (part VII, continuing on from the six parts of the original album), is an absolute tour de force, one of the best tracks Jarre has produced. Listening to it the first time was a bit like the return of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parable_of_the_Prodigal_Son">Prodigal Son</a>. Part VIII is the obligatory single in the vein of Oxygene part IV: it’s not terrible, but a bit arthritic for the age in which it was produced.</p>

<p>The rest of the album doesn’t have the same vitality, but isn’t bad by any means, and Oxygene 7 - 13 must overall be considered a return to genuine form. And yet, well, when you get down to it musical sequels (Tubular Bells II is another example, maybe Bat out of Hell 2, too?!) are creatively redundant, and a bit self-indulgent. Also, Jarre had already produced an Oxygene sequel in the form of Equinoxe, so why go back there in 1997, or again in 2016, with Oxygene 3? Nostalgia and sales.</p>

<h2 id="not-embarrassing-music-video-1">Not embarrassing music video</h2>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lVEAk5Lpwf0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>No embarrassment in this video, but not much of anything else, either.</p>

<h1 id="the-latter-years">The latter years</h1>

<p>Perhaps five years ago I gave Jarre’s 2000s work a cursory listen through on Spotify. I both don’t remember and didn’t think very much of it. Then there’s the huge Electronica compilation: a series of collaborations with other electronic luminaries. If you’re feeling charitable, such a project is an admirable piece of outreach and limelight sharing; more cynically it could be viewed as a waning talent collaborating to maintain relevancy.</p>

<p>In more recent years, however, Jarre has experienced a relative renaissance: Equinoxe Infinity is actually pretty listenable, and Oxygene 3, while more dour than I’d prefer, is decent enough. But for me the stand out album of the past three (nearly four) decades is the 2021 album Amazonia. Intended as background music to a photographic exhibition, it’s a vivid and revelatory piece of ambient music, featuring numerous field recordings from the Amazon basin. It’s a mix of Zoolook and Waiting for Cousteau, more understated than the former, and less rigid than the latter. All the while it dodges the well-worn paths of Deep Forest and Enigma. To my mind it’s the most successful Jarre’s been at engaging with the minimal sensibility of the last 30 years of electronica. Sadly he followed it up with a VR performance in Notre Dame, or somesuch. But still, it gives me encouragement that something new of interest might come out in future, though Jarre is pushing 75.</p>

<h1 id="what-to-make-of-it-all">What to make of it all</h1>

<p>I think it would be fair to say that the work of Jean Michel Jarre has left me with mixed feelings. Looking at it really positively, Jarre’s music taught me a lot about what I liked and disliked in music generally: Oxygene and Zoolook I enjoyed without reservation, and will happily defend to this day. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iZivR39Opmo&amp;t=60s">The overly cheesy synth solo on Industrial Revolution</a> I enjoyed on first listen, but eventually I came to see as hollow and unearned (nice performance from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_Art_(band)">Dominique Perrier</a>, though). As for Rendez-Vous Part IV, well I always found that as intellectually and emotionally as nutritious as cardboard.</p>

<p>But having listened to a lot of electronic music since then (mostly 1970 - 2000), I will say that at his best, Jarre is a genuine giant. And at his worst, he’s a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurotrash_(term)">Eurotrash</a> producer of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cirque_du_Soleil">Cirque du Soleil</a> background music. Now I suppose his commitment to demotic electronica is admirably of-the-people, but that doesn’t detract from the resulting music being emotionally shallow and frequently embarrassing. It seems to me that Jarre really wanted to be a rock star, and boy was that an instinct he should have resisted.</p>

<p>It’s interesting to compare Jarre with his fellow travellers. But who exactly are they? Growing up, Vangelis seemed to be his most obvious peer, but with greater familiarity of the Greek master’s work, he was more varied and less electronic than he superifically seemed. (Boy could he make some amazing sounds with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamaha_CS-80">CS-80</a>, though…) Since I recently wrote about Tangerine Dream, lets compare Jarre compare with Tangerine Dream founder Edgar Froese? The difference in temperament is amusingly stereotypical: Jarre and his Gallic flair versus the phlemagtically earnest German Froese. I’d say Jarre is probably a more talented composer, but Froese had the more clear-minded ethos behind his work. Indeed, aside from the ecological motivations behind Oxygene (and Michel Granger’s remarkable cover painting), Jarre’s career seems to have been an endless search for a <em>raison d’etre</em>.</p>

<p>A less contemporaenous but more apt comparison might be with the American producer <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moby">Moby</a>, who has had similar lapses in taste, and who also desperately wants to be a star. This time Jarre comes off rather better for the comparison; flawed as he is, he’s never been as undignified as Moby.</p>

<p>Regardless of how mixed I’ve found Jarre’s legacy, he’s one of life’s winners, anyway, so you know, <em>french shrug</em>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Growing up in the early 80s I was aware of synthesized sound. I don’t know why I found the bloops interesting - perhaps it was the common presence of “synthetic electronic sound” in science fiction TV shows that made it so evocative to me. Older people seemed to find electronic sounds cold and alienating, but for me they were beguiling.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sturm und Drang mit Tangerine Dream</title><link href="/2022/05/12/tangerine-dream.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sturm und Drang mit Tangerine Dream" /><published>2022-05-12T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-05-12T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/2022/05/12/tangerine-dream</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/05/12/tangerine-dream.html"><![CDATA[<p>After a cheery frolic through the worlds of JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure and K-pop, I turn now to something very serious indeed: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tangerine_Dream">Tangerine Dream</a>.</p>

<p>For those who haven’t yet made Tangerine Dream their personal religion, they were (at least for the period in which I am interested in them) an electronic rock group. Founded and principally organised by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgar_Froese">Edgar Froese</a>, Tangerine Dream were stalwarts of the so-called (but not by the participants) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Krautrock">Krautrock</a> movement. They formed in Berlin in the late 1960s, and are still a going concern today. In all Tangerine Dream has released in excess of a hundred of studio and concert albums, as well as numerous film soundtracks. Of this total output I’ve heard perhaps 10%, because my primary interest is in the group’s early 1970s albums (what I’ll call the “classic” period), which have had a profound influence on my thinking about music, and indeed the cosmos.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/td/tangerine-dream-band-cathedral.jpg" width="600" alt="Picture of classic-era Tangerine Dream" title="Picture of classic-era Tangerine Dream" />
    <figcaption>Classic-era Tangerine Dream prior to a cathedral concert. From left to right: Edgar "Saxon Aslan" Froese, Christopher "Goth Womble" Franke, Peter "Skater Girl" Baumann. Credit: <a href="https://www.eastgate-music.shop/en/contact/index.asp">Eastgate Music</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="my-personal-dreamtime">My personal dreamtime</h1>

<p>For whatever reason I always found electronic sound interesting, and started actively investigating it from the age of 15. I can’t remember how I learned of Tangerine Dream’s existence. Maybe it was because their CDs frequently turned up in the library category “electronic”. Whatever the reason I started listening to Tangerine Dream from early 1992.</p>

<p>In the age of Spotify I can find and listen to Tangerine Dream’s albums in seconds, but in the early 90s physical media was all there was, and there wasn’t much available at that. I could have ordered what I wanted through music shops on “import”, but I didn’t have the money to pay the required premium. To be more scrupulously honest I had money but optimised my spending - where quality was even - on quantity. I could buy three classical music tapes for one import CD, so I did that.</p>

<p>The upshot is that I had to be patient. One thing to be said about this scenario is that it made me continually hungry for music in a way I am not today. (I want to add a sentence about how this gave kids of my generation moral fibre which today’s youth lack. Oh, it turns out I have added this sentence. Well, let me add the caveat that I mean it only half seriously.)</p>

<p>Because I had to take what I could find, my initial sampling of Tangerine Dream’s works was quite random. It soon became clear that the group’s music came in two categories: the 1970s albums that I mostly found Very Interesting, and the 1980s albums that tended to be Bland and Uninteresting. I now provide a survey of albums in the former category.</p>

<h2 id="phaedra">Phaedra</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/phaedra.png" width="300" alt="Phaedra album cover" title="Phaedra album cover" /></p>

<p>Unlike electronic music I’d listened to previously (Vangelis, Jean Michel Jarre), which was orderly and reasonably pleasant, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phaedra_(album)">Phaedra</a> was something new: scary. Phaedra’s eponymous track, dribbled in uneasily out of silence, with a sinister repeating cascade of notes soon dominating. This melodic tumble gradually evolved, becoming faster and losing its tuning (voltage-controlled synthesizers were notorious for this), before expiring into a bleak soundscape haunted by demented howlings.</p>

<p>The rest of the album’s tracks weren’t quite as hypnotically terrifying, but just as impactful. The unsnappily named “Mysterious Semblance at the Strand of Nightmares” sounded to me like an organist warming up to play at my funeral, while “Movements of a Visionary” skittled and rattled with agreeable mania. The short finale, “Sequent C” ended the album on a desolate and comfortless note. It was a vivid experience and I was instantly hooked.</p>

<p>I pored over album’s liner notes. The three members (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Franke">Chris Franke</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Baumann">Peter Baumann</a>, and founder Froese) all seemed to be playing something called a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/EMS_VCS_3">VCS3</a>, and something that was science fictionally named “mellotron”. Finally, Chris Franke played an instrument called a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moog_synthesizer">Moog synthesizer</a>. None of this meant anything to me, but I was deeply impressed.</p>

<p>Phaedra was uncompromising but I found in it something of me, or something that, through familiarity, felt me-ish. It might have helped that at the time I was suffering from (in my unprofessional estimation) clinical depression; I was certainly finding the latter half of my teen years quite trying. I don’t want to over-stress this, as I think most teenagers are on the edge of some mental crisis or another - it’s a pretty trying time for everyone. But I think my personal gloom does explain my attraction to Phaedra: the baleful mood of the album provided me with a kind of solace. (At the time, other kids were probably deriving the same sort of consolation from say Nirvana, but I found Nirvana nihilistic and comfortless.)</p>

<h2 id="zeit">Zeit</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/zeit.png" width="300" alt="Zeit album cover" title="Zeit album cover" /></p>

<p>Four months later in August ‘92 that I hit my next Tangerine Dream jackpot: the 1972 double album <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zeit_(Tangerine_Dream_album)">Zeit</a> (German for time, if you weren’t aware) on glorious single cassette. Playing it revealed (rather hissily) 70 minutes of cosmic mystery, or, as the group pretentiously subtitled it, “a largo in four movements”.</p>

<p>I listened to Zeit for the first time in my bedroom on a Saturday afternoon. Outside it was a brightly sunny winter’s day, but inside my room the tension was building. As the first cello drones of the first track (“Birth of the Liquid Pleiades”, is the un-understated title), my mood was so hyperbolically neurotic that I was convinced the music was going to drive me mad. But I persisted, and the searing battle between four cellos and a Moog synthesizer eventually subsided into a more peaceful organ interlude. The next track, “Nebulous Dawn” was a more straightforward alien soundscape: a bit like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebe_and_Louis_Barron#Forbidden_Planet">Barrons’ soundtrack to Forbidden Planet</a>. It conveyed what its title suggests, but I found it a little static for its length, and I think it’s the weakest of the four “movements”.</p>

<p>Turning the tape over, the third track, “Origin of Supernatural Probabilities”, had much more propulsion, with hypnotic synth burbling dominating proceedings, bookended by mysterious guitar chords. It was the most dynamic track on the album. Finally, there’s the title track, a cold, cosmic shimmer, occasionally intruded by the plaintive squeals of what sounded to me like a dying cat. Then it gradually faded away, like the heat death of the universe, but also strangely cathartic. After the tape ran out, I felt strangely triumphant. I’d survived the encounter, and felt transformed by the journey.</p>

<p>Zeit has become for me a sort of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Desert_Island_Discs">Desert Island Disc</a>. It’s not necessarily better than Phaedra, but it had a greater emotional impact on me. It’s the sort of album that I’d hope would be playing me out as I shuffle off into eternity.</p>

<h2 id="electronic-meditation">Electronic Meditation</h2>

<p>The next Tangerine Dream album I caught up with was the band’s first, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_Meditation">Electronic Meditation</a>, from 1970. From the title I was expecting to hear a Zeit-like ambient exploration, but what I heard was fairly middling stoner rock, with not a single bloop in earshot. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conrad_Schnitzler">Conrad Schnitzler</a>’s manic cello sawing is admirable, but there’s just too much hippie flutework. (It’s not I dislike rock flutes - mad respect for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ian_Anderson">Ian Anderson</a> - it’s just that in this case it wasn’t up to much.)</p>

<p>In Tangerine Dream’s defence, I’ve discovered since that the album title was supplied by their label boss, and the recordings were demos not intended by the band for release.</p>

<h2 id="atem">Atem</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/atem.png" width="300" alt="Atem album cover" title="Atem album cover" /></p>

<p>In ~November 1992 I accessed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atem_(album)">Atem</a> through my friend Mike Lindley. He played it through to me and embarrassed me a bit by pointing out at one point a fizz of white noises sounded like someone having a shower (he was right). The album kicked off with thunderous drumming and organwork which reached a crescendo before falling away. The rest of the track was a Zeit-like eerie reverie. Splendid stuff! The second track, Fauni Gena, was sort of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pr%C3%A9lude_%C3%A0_l%27apr%C3%A8s-midi_d%27un_faune">Prélude à l’après-midi d’un faune</a> but with actual nature recordings and rather more sinister undertones. “Circulation of Events” is a further droney meditation, while the finale, Wahn, is a short burst of tribal drumming and shouting that brings proceedings to a dramatic close.</p>

<p>Rather strangely Atem became for me a soundtrack for the summer of 1992-1993.</p>

<h2 id="alpha-centauri">Alpha Centauri</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/alpha-centauri.png" width="300" alt="Alpha Centauri album cover" title="Alpha Centauri album cover" /></p>

<p>It was another year before I found my next classic Tangerine Dream album. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_Centauri_(album)">Alpha Centauri</a> from 1971 still predates Tangerine Dream’s wholesale taking up of synthesisers. There’s still rather too much flute action, and listless jamming, but the band has least ascended into out of space, and the album is more thought out than its predecessor, Electronic Meditation. All up it’s a transitional album: not quite top tier but still a lot of fun.</p>

<h2 id="rubycon">Rubycon</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/rubycon.png" width="300" alt="Rubycon album cover" title="Rubycon album cover" /></p>

<p>Rubycon was Tangerine Dream’s followup to Phaedra, featuring two long sides of lushly produced sequencer-propelled music. It’s a prototype for what is called (rather pompously to my mind) the ‘Berlin School’ style, popularised more by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Klaus_Schulze">Klaus Schulze</a> (recently RIP, an early member of Tangerine Dream) and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manuel_G%C3%B6ttsching">Manuel Gottsching</a> (Schulze’s bandmate in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ash_Ra_Tempel">Ash Ra Tempel</a>).</p>

<p>When I first listened to Rubycon (parts 1 and 2) on my 20th birthday in 1995, I found the album a bit disappointing because the two sides have largely identical structures, and I found that quite flat compared to the variety of previous albums. Over time I’ve come to appreciate the album more (it’s great to work to), but I would say it’s the weakest of the ‘72 - ‘75 albums.</p>

<h2 id="stratosfear">Stratosfear</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/stratosfear.png" width="300" alt="Stratosfear album cover" title="Stratosfear album cover" /></p>

<p>1976’s Stratosfear marked a stylistic change into what I would dismiss as “synth prog”. Gone were the ambiguous drone washes and bloopy bits, and in came focused arrangements and guitar licks intended to sound like guitar. Stratosfear acts as a kind of bookend in that it was with this album that “classic” Tangerine Dream abruptly ended.</p>

<h2 id="thru-metamorphic-rock">Thru Metamorphic Rock</h2>

<p>One night in ‘93 I tape-recorded an ambientish show on my local student radio station. It was so late at I went to bed after pressing record. When I listened back I heard some ambienty/world music tracks for a while, and then this new, dramatic piece. It began with a whooshing, skittering noise rhythm, soon followed by a propulsive, emphatic sequencer burble which cascaded urgently for about ten minutes. I thought “wow, this is great”.</p>

<p>The DJ didn’t announce what the track’s name was - it’s possible they had fallen asleep at the mixer - so I had no idea at the time what the music was and who it was by. I guessed it was contemporary, not really knowing what contemporary sounded like. Thereafter I’d play the recording back every so often, wondering whether I’d ever find out who made it.</p>

<p>Perhaps a year later, I stayed up late one night to watch <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Mann">Michael Mann</a>’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thief_(film)">Thief</a> solely because it had a Tangerine Dream score. About halfway through I was astonished to hear the track I’d recorded off the radio, playing during a tense scene where safe-cracker <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Caan">James Caan</a> is racing against time to break into a bank vault. I was astonished. Of course it was Tangerine Dream! How could I not know it was Tangerine Dream?</p>

<p>With further investigation I found out the extremely apt name for this track: Thru Metamorphic Rock. The track originally appeared on the band’s 1979 Force Majeure album. The rest of the record is sort of synthy prog rock so the sequencer fury of the track proper is something of an outlier, hearking back to the Phaedra/Rubycon era.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/K7ZawnFFUYs?start=279" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<h1 id="who-the-band-were">Who the band were</h1>

<p>I’ve rambled on about Tangerine Dream’s albums without really going into who they were and their historical context. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tangerine_Dream">Wikipedia will do a better job</a>, but I’m also happy to give you my take.</p>

<p>Tangerine Dream were part of a wider movement of experimental German rock in the late 60s and early 70s, designated in English by the slightly perjorative (if memorable) term “Krautrock”. The Krautrock groups were influenced by a heady combination of Anglo-American psychedelic rock and the European avant-garde, but eventually developed their own original voices and wonderful and varied music.</p>

<p>The early Tangerine Dream sound of (at least that recorded on their first album, Electronic Meditation) seems heavily influenced by contemporary <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd">Pink Floyd</a>, and this influence continued to be felt in Tangerine Dream’s classic albums. (To my mind Tangerine Dream eclipsed the Floyd, in that they did the stuff I like about Floyd - cosmic wonder and out there sounds - better than Floyd did, while steering clear of Floyd’s blues-bound psychedelia and dreary middle-class miserablism. Pink Floyd fans may disagree…)</p>

<p>Tangerine Dream’s second album, Alpha Centauri, was still identifiably rock, but a cosmic focus was now apparent, and you can hear hints of the sound to come. By 1972 and Zeit, all rock instrumentation had been dispensed with (save for some sparingly used guitar) and the album’s sound was primarily built from long organ drones and synth wobbles. Double albums were a bit of early 70s prog indulgence, but I think Zeit was a statement that genuinely needed the extra run time. Given what had gone before, it was a very audacious change of direction.</p>

<p>Atem was a return to more structured sound (and the return of drumming, if more tribal than rock), but Zeit had indelibly changed the group’s trajectory. Atem is a more straightforward album than Zeit, but still a world removed from Alpha Centauri. The quality is about the same as Zeit, and perhaps a little more assured.</p>

<p>After many years operating in relative obscurity in the German underground scene, Tangerine Dream eventually found success in the UK after being championed by influential DJ <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Peel">John Peel</a>, and then signed to Virgin Records. With Phaedra’s release the group found itself having a genuine UK hit (it reached number 15 in the UK album charts, which is a credit to the open-mindedness of the music-buying public of the time). Successful Europeans and (crucially) American tours followed, and Tangerine Dream began composing Hollywood film soundtracks, starting with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Friedkin">William Friedkin</a>’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sorcerer_(soundtrack)">Sorcerer</a> in 1977. Meanwhile, the group adapted to changes in technology and taste in the 1980s by forging a crystalline, new-Age-friendly musical style. The group have maintained a consistent following ever since.</p>

<p>In recent years the relevance of Tangerine Dream has arguably increased. The recent craze for DIY modular synthesizers represents a return to vogue of 1970s synth production. (It’s questionable whether the resulting music represents any advance on what Tangerine Dream and other groups achieved 50 years ago.) More directly, the Tangerine Dream’s work has been used in media like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grand_Theft_Auto_V">Grand Theft Auto</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_Stranger_Things">Stranger Things</a>.</p>

<h1 id="later-archaeological-discoveries">Later archaeological discoveries</h1>

<p>Back to my personal history with Tangerine Dream. After my early to mid 90s exploration of the, there was a long period where I didn’t find any new material. Starting in the late 2000s, and through to today, however, I’ve periodically collected more artefacts from the group’s classic period.</p>

<h2 id="tangerine-tree-and-leaves">Tangerine Tree (and leaves)</h2>

<p>In the late 2000s I learned that in the early 2000s many live recordings of Tangerine Dream concerts had been collected and released gratis (with the band’s blessing). This project, known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tangerine_Tree">Tangerine Tree</a> contains a handful of recordings from the band’s classic era:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1lB1yt7YkkQ">pre-Zeit concert in Frankfurt</a> (1971)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sFl5vmA8LJE">Some feline groaning in Ossiach</a> (1971)</li>
  <li>The <a href="https://www.voices-in-the-net.de/ttree052.htm">“Klangwald?”</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zbuZ6qpW-m4">performance?</a> (1972)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NqJUoNl0hB4">Saint Ouen</a> (1973)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BCPLrJvhSLU">Berlin</a> (1973)</li>
</ul>

<p>Because Tangerine Dream’s music of the time was completely improvised, each concert is pretty much unique. Better still, the artistic quality - if not the recording quality - is high, so these recordings represent a significant expansion of Tangerine Dream’s recorded work. For me they have been a welcome discovery in middle age.</p>

<h2 id="soundtracks">Soundtracks</h2>

<p>There are also a couple of soundtracks Tangerine Dream made during the classic era that are worth checking out:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=h3-83fTszRc">Vampira soundtrack</a> (1971) - proto-Zeit soundtrack to what I guess would be a vampire movie. Feels more H.P. Lovecraft than Bela Lugosi, and that’s a good thing.</li>
  <li>Oedipus Tyrannus - See below.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="edgars-solo-albums">Edgar’s solo albums</h2>

<p>In addition to Tangerine Tree, there’s also Edgar Froese’s three mid-70s solo albums, which further expand the classic Tangerine Dream corpus.</p>

<h3 id="aqua">Aqua</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/td/aqua.jpg" width="300" alt="Aqua album cover" title="Aqua album cover" /></p>

<p>Froese’s first solo album is 1974’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aqua_(Edgar_Froese_album)">Aqua</a>. It’s a pretty solid collection, commencing with the swirly, side-spanning title track. Flipping the disc over and there’s the warm, robust, hypnotic burbles of Berlin-soundy Panorphelia. After the suitably galactic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NGC_891">NGC 891</a>, the album is concluded with the pulsing Upland.</p>

<p>Aqua was recorded roughly around the time of Phaedra, which I find fascinating because the album has nothing of Phaedra’s bleak intensity.</p>

<h3 id="epsilon-in-malaysian-pale">Epsilon in Malaysian Pale</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/td/epsilon-in-malaysian-pale.jpg" width="300" alt="Epsilon in Malaysian Pale cover" title="Epsilon in Malaysian Pale cover" /></p>

<p>1975’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epsilon_in_Malaysian_Pale">Epsilon in Malaysian Pale</a> (Epsilon in Malaysian Pale) is strikingly similar to Rubycon, in that both albums consist of two side-long sequencer-driven tracks. But the albums differ in two respects: the arrangement and production on Epsilon in Malaysian Pale is more rudimentary: at one point the tape signal drops out completely. (All of Tangerine Dream’s early albums were comparatively low-fi; Rubycon is the first to avoid loudness clipping, obvious edits, or, in Zeit’s case, the sound of a creaking chair caught on microphone.) It’s tempting to wonder if Epsilon in Malaysian Pale started life as a demo for Rubycon.</p>

<p>The second difference is that despite Rubycon being considerably more polished, Epsilon in Malaysian Pale feels more dynamic and substantial. I don’t know exactly which album was recorded first, but Epsilon in Malaysian Pale feels like a sketch for Rubycon. If so, the sketch turned out better than the finished product.</p>

<p>Epsilon in Malaysian Pale was championed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Bowie">David Bowie</a> as the soundtrack to his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Bowie#1976%E2%80%931979:_Berlin_era">time in Berlin</a> in the late 1970s, and I think the album’s cathartic mood maps well to Bowie’s Berlin rehabilitation after years of drug abuse and rock’n’roll chaos. (Supplemental factoid: Edgar Froese helped Bowie find a flat in Berlin).</p>

<h3 id="macula-transfer-and-stuntman">Macula Transfer and Stuntman</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/td/macular-transfer.jpg" width="300" alt="Macula Transfer album cover" title="Macula Transfer album cover" /></p>

<p><img src="/assets/td/stuntman.jpg" width="300" alt="Stuntman album cover" title="Stuntman album cover" /></p>

<p>Froese’s 1976 album <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macula_Transfer">Macula Transfer</a> is also worth checking out. It’s not as accomplished as Aqua or Epsilon in Malaysian Pale, and it’s slightly transitional, but it retains enough of the classic sound to be considered part of what I might call the “supporting” canon.</p>

<p>There’s one other Froese composition of interest: the title track from his 1979 album <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuntman_(Edgar_Froese_album)">Stuntman</a>. By this stage Froese had switched to a formal (as in structured), commercially-oriented style almost diametrically opposed to the freeform explorations of Zeit and Atem. But Stuntman’s title track is a winningly cheerful burble that is both <em>sooo</em> 70s but also from the glorious future that never was. (Oddly, I first heard the Stuntman track all the way back in 1987 when it was used as the theme music to the BBC Science Magazine radio programme. I didn’t know it was Edgar until 30 years later, but after the Thru Metamorphic Rock episode, I took this discovery more in my stride.)</p>

<p>Froese’s classic era solo works help us measure his contribution to the overall sound of the band. While the production on Aqua and Epsilon in Malaysian Pale is more stripped back, the mood is sufficiently similar to Tangerine Dream to suggest (in the absence of solo material from Franke and Baumann during the period) that Froese was the prime creative force in the group.</p>

<h2 id="oedipus-tyrannus">Oedipus Tyrannus</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/td/oedipus_tyrannus.jpg" width="300" alt="Oedipus Tyrannus album cover" title="Oedipus Tyrannus album cover" /></p>

<p>Finally, there’s <a href="https://voices-in-the-net.de/oedipus_tyrannus.htm">a lost Tangerine Dream album</a>: in 1974 Tangerine Dream recorded music for a performance of Oedipus Rex at the Chichester Festival. The 70 minute suite was originally intended for as an album release, but was eventually shelved. Some parts got circulated in bootleg format, but Oedpius Tyrannus didn’t get a full release until 2019.</p>

<p>Oedipus Tyrannus is absolutely fascinating. The first track, Overture, contains elements hearkening back to Zeit, while “Act 1” and “Act 2: Battle” are more reminiscent of Phaedra. “Act2: Baroque” simultaneously hints forward to Stratosfear and back Atem. “Act 2: Zeus” is a throwback to Zeit again. The beginning of “Act 3” was used for the conclusion of Rubycon part 2, and later there’s some furious sequencer clatter (with resonant squelch reminiscent of acid house!).</p>

<p>So what to make of all that? As background misery for a Greek tragedy the music makes perfect sense, and there are plenty of great moments, but it just doesn’t quite gel as an album.</p>

<p>With all that said, Oedipus Tyrannus remains intriguing for being a stylistic compendium Tangerine Dream’s work to that point, without having a distinct identity of its own. Despite that it’s still good to have it.</p>

<h1 id="what-do-i-get-out-of-tangerine-dream">What do I get out of Tangerine Dream?</h1>

<p>This is a personal outline of why Tangerine Dream means so much to me. I should say at the outset that is my subjective viewpoint, and I don’t even expect hardcore Tangerine Dream fans to necessarily agree with me.</p>

<p>For me classic Tangerine Dream is the intersection of the following phenomena:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Sonic open-mindedness steeped in 1960s German avant-garde</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychedelia">Psychedelia</a></li>
  <li>A strong desire to explore <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sublime_(philosophy)">the sublime</a></li>
</ol>

<p>Point 1 we’ve already discussed. Point 2. is almost too obvious to mention, but I will point out that while I’ve never used psychedelics and wouldn’t dare presume to understand what it’s like to consume them, I do get a sense that Tangerine Dream’s classic era music is the result of some profound <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychonautics">psychonautical experiences</a>.</p>

<p>As for point 3, there are moments in Tangerine Dream’s music where it evokes both grandeur and horror, which lines up well with the Romantic conception of the Sublime.</p>

<p>Tangerine Dream’s music is rooted in traditional Western tonality, although in the Classic albums there’s usually some element of discord present that hints at psychological extremes. Perhaps that’s why it appealed to me as a teenager. Even when the music is more quiet or serene, there’s always an undercurrent of drama (indeed literally so with Oedipus Tyrannus).</p>

<p>The drama and earnestness of classic Tangerine Dream has perhaps made them less hip (if more hippie) than the other two great Krautrock bands, Kraftwerk and Can. And I should say though that the classic albums are not without fault. Some of the bloops and bleeps are now dated and quaint. Zeit clearly has some debts to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gy%C3%B6rgy_Ligeti">Ligeti</a> (and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2001:_A_Space_Odyssey_(soundtrack)#Music">Kubrick</a>, for that matter). And there’s the lingering Pink Floyd influence…</p>

<p>Even so, classic Tangerine Dream remains for me a companion for life. Much of that is perhaps tied to being 17 when I first heard them, but I feel the singular feature of the band is that they meant every note of what they did. I can’t know precisely what Tangerine Dream were really about, but I’ve always found their early vision utterly compelling.</p>

<p>I’ve spoken about religious devotion to Tangerine Dream, and that’s a bit of exaggeration for comic effect, but they are a group a take more seriously than any other. This may be an odd way to end up, but that’s where I am.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After a cheery frolic through the worlds of JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure and K-pop, I turn now to something very serious indeed: Tangerine Dream.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">K/DA and Blackpink</title><link href="/2022/04/25/kda.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="K/DA and Blackpink" /><published>2022-04-25T00:00:00+12:00</published><updated>2022-04-25T00:00:00+12:00</updated><id>/2022/04/25/kda</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/04/25/kda.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p>While viewing JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure MMD videos I stumbled across some JoJo dancings choreographed to songs by a group called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K/DA">K/DA</a>. The music was sufficiently impressive that I decided to watch the original videos, discovering that K/DA is an animated “girl” group comprised of characters from a video game called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/League_of_Legends">League of Legends</a>. I then watched <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=de-xgNEsE3I">a useful explainer about the group</a> and learned that K/DA’s western producers intentionally wrote the songs to emulate the K-pop genre. This essay is a personal (which is to say idiosyncratic and unreliable) exploration of K/DA and my experience of K-pop.</p>

<h1 id="k-pop-and-its-part-in-my-downfall">K-pop and its part in my downfall</h1>

<p>Because K/DA is K-pop-oriented, it makes sense to examine K-pop first. Well, Wikipedia can give you a more <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/K-pop">sensible explanation of K-pop</a> than I ever could, so instead I’ll yammer on about how I got into it.</p>

<p>Going waaay back in time to the late 2000s, my wife and I began watching K dramas. (We’d watched lots of HK dramas, and a J and T drama or two, so it’s not as random as it might seem.) K-dramas proved to be a gateway drug to K variety shows, specifically <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Running_Man_(South_Korean_TV_series)">Running Man</a>, which was very popular across asia in the early 2010s. Running Man frequently featured K-pop singers, but while we did take some interest K-pop singers who had both been in dramas <em>and</em> appeared on Running Man, it wasn’t until that epoch-defining revelation of PSY’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gangnam_Style">Gangnam Style</a> in 2012 that I began listening in earnest.</p>

<p>(Look, I’ll readily concede that now ten years have passed, I might have gotten a bit too into that curious phenomenon. But you know, you had to be there, man.)</p>

<p>After some explanatory listening, I found I was more interested in the girl groups. The reason for this is that while the boy groups seemed stuck permanently in 1988 making <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_jack_swing">New Jack Swing</a> singles (one exception: Big Bang), the girl groups tended to have more angst and silliness in their music. I think this is because while all K pop tends to a female (or gay) audience, boy and girl groups have different functions. Boy idols are there to be unthreatening (if also unattainable) love interests, while girl idols are friends to admire for their poise and skill and/or relatable feelings.</p>

<p>Is this characterisation too simplistic? Probably, but I suspect it’s a reasonable percentage of the truth.</p>

<p>In 2012 the biggest girl group was <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Girls%27_Generation">SNSD</a>, but I preferred more eccentric groups like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orange_Caramel">Orange Caramel</a>, and (later) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crayon_Pop">Crayon Pop</a>; or the more EDMish outfits like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/F(x)_(musical_group)">f(x)</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2NE1">2NE1</a>.</p>

<p>I kept an eye on the K-pop scene for a few years, but around 2016 I began to lose interest in all K phenomena. With K dramas I’d seen as many variations on “downtrodden but plucky female implausibly pursued by multiple <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chaebol">chaebol</a> heir suitors” as I could tolerate. With K variety, after a few hundred episodes of Running man the formula got pretty stale for me - as I think it would for most people after that long. As for K-pop, the music was also beginning to feel a bit samey (and this is still true for me more than half a decade later). I was also put off by the petty (and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burning_Sun_scandal">not so petty</a> scandals continually bubbling up (I used to think Korean “netizens” were the most judgemental people on Earth, until Facebook and Twitter deranged the brains of Westerners). But I was most demoralised by the steady rate of K-pop suicides, esp Goo Hara of Kara and Sulli of f(x). I began to feel complicit in the harm K-pop caused its performers, and I stopped listening.</p>

<p>Until last year. My K pop curiosity was reignited when I learned that boy group <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BTS">BTS</a> had topped the Billboard charts in the US. In the mid 2010s I thought a girl group might have a chance of doing this, at some point, but never a boy group (even one with <a href="https://www.usbtsarmy.com/">their own army</a>). Curiouser still, the number one hit song in question, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gdZLi9oWNZg">Dynamite</a>, was the same old New Jack Swing. Weird! That said, the BTS chaps seem nice - <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GJZeMgqQMjA">at least when they interact with robots</a> - and I wish them well.</p>

<p>But since I’d taken the trouble to investigate BTS, I thought I might as well learn more about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blackpink">Blackpink</a>, the pre-eminent K-pop girl group who had debuted and risen to the top while I was off the K-pop bandwagon.</p>

<p>Blackpink are successors to YG Entertainment’s 2NE1, who unceremoniously expired when one of their members experienced a rather minor drug scandal back in 2015. Blackpink have largely continued where 2NE1 left off. The group is comprised of mostly-singers Ji Soo and Rose, and mostly-rappers Jennie and Lisa. Like many K-pop groups, Blackpink’s composition is cosmopolitan in outlook: Lisa is Thai, while Jennie spent her formative years in New Zealand and Rose was raised in Australia.</p>

<p>Over the past six years Blackpink have assembled numerous shock-and-awe singles. My favourites are Ddu-du Ddu-du (see below), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ioNng23DkIM">How You Like that</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dISNgvVpWlo">Whistle</a>.</p>

<p>The songs tend to start out with petulant rapping by Jennie and Lisa, before modulating to  angsty singing by Ji Soo and Rose, and then onto the chorus. I confess I tend to spend the singing bits waiting for the next rap segment, but the songs are usually well-constructed, and there are numerous excursions into unexpected territory that have me going “whaaat!?” - in a good way. Basically they’re a riot.</p>

<p>And then we come to the videos. YG has produced some glitzy stuff in the past (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AAbokV76tkU">take that!</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j7_lSP8Vc3o">and that!</a>), but those vids seem minimalist in comparison to the almost baroque production value of recent Blackpink outings. Ddu-du Ddu-du has some particularly eye-poppingly odd moments.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IHNzOHi8sJs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>During my investigations I discovered that Blackpink had a <a href="https://www.netflix.com/watch/81106901?trackId=255824129">Netflix doco</a> - unthinkable for a US-based media company to be producing a few years ago, but all too predictable now. “Blackpink: Light up the Sky” is a reasonably frank portrayal of life under the K-pop regime. (To give you a very brief idea of how the system works, aspiring adolescent K-Poppers are scouted - usually in shopping malls - by a management agency, and then auditioned. Those who make the grade live in an agency dormitory for several years, being trained around the clock. Wages are slim, and chances of unceremonious disposal are high. Gradually the promising coalesce into prospective groups, until finally the tight-knit, loyal, battle-hardened and success-hungry Chosen are anointed. Whatever else you might think about it - and I think quite a lot about it, actually - it’s a practice that gets results.)</p>

<p>I was suspicious that the doco was purely propaganda, and I imagine there was much that was glossed over, but I got the impression the group were able to recount their struggles with genuine candour. We may not have gotten the whole story, but if you aspired to K-pop glory you wouldn’t watch “Light up the Sky” and conclude that it’s all sweetness and light.</p>

<p>Here’s an aside: watching the doco, it occurred to me that Blackpink’s training must have occurred during 2NE1’s final years. Were 2NE1 aware that YG’s trainees would eventually succeed them? How could they not? For if not these partictrainees, then eventually others would… It’s a tough business.</p>

<p>If being a K-pop trainee seems harsh, it’s nothing compared to being successful: 18 hour days, endless appearances at fan meets, lengthy video shoots, and trying to seem interesting but also down to earth in highly-scripted media appearences.</p>

<p>But wait, there’s more! Long international tours, the constant fear of physical attacks by obsessive fans or fending off sexual “attention” from sleazy “entertainment figures”, and the stress of attaining and retaining lucrative product endorsements. Your words and actions need to justify the loyalty of your fans, your family, your bandmates, your country, and those you work with in your agency. There’s constant risk of ground down by excessive online opprobrium. Having a personal life is extremely difficult; a love life is forbidden - you must remain in mint condition for the duration of your youth.</p>

<p>With all that going on you can see why mental health crises, drug scandals, and suicides are quite common in the K-pop world.</p>

<p>So far Blackpink seem to have survived, but there will inevitably be a point when they will drift from being “it” to becoming “was”. In the doco the group’s members seemed to think that all the sacrifices have been worth it; I hope that’s true and continues to so. They can take comfort in knowing that at this point it’s going to be a hell of a group that surpasses them.</p>

<h2 id="hang-on">Hang on</h2>

<p>So I’ve spent a lot of time cataloguing some of the participants and many of the crimes of K-pop, but I should point out that manufactured pop groups, and indeed every popular musical combo at any time and place, has been subject to some level of exploitation. The difference, I would argue, is that western kids are less likely to put up with K-pop-style regimentation, and so aren’t subjected to those excesses, whereas the communal conformity of Korean culture tends to increase the likelihood of everybody going along with things until harm happens.</p>

<p>Actually, I’d <em>like</em> to thing that Western kids would be less susceptible, but I’m not sure they that’s actually true. Hmmm.</p>

<h1 id="kda">K/DA</h1>

<p>Now we’ve got a sense of the high-stakes tension of a real K-pop group, let us decompress somewhat and consider a virtual one. I vaguely heard of K/DA when they debuted in 2018, but this was during my “over it” K-pop dark age, and I could’t be bothered investigating. But in late 2021, thanks to a tenuous JJBA connection, I was now in a place to give it a whirl.</p>

<p>So K/DA is a virtual girl group featuring four characters from the online game League of Legends characters. The group’s music is produced in house by League of Legends publisher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riot_Games">Riot Games</a>. I’ve never played League of Legends and have no idea who the group’s “members” actually are. I could spend two minutes looking them up, but I think it would be more humorous to simply characterise them as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the gritty, urban one</li>
  <li>the cocktail bar singer</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Melanie_C">Sporty Spice</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kumiho">Foxy Lady</a></li>
</ul>

<p>To underscore how out of depth I am in analysing K/DA, I should point out that my prior reference points for music made by animated entities are the following:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h9nE2spOw_o" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/159063171?h=e17ebd1d93&amp;byline=0" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Wish me luck!</p>

<p>The first K/DA single was a song called Pop/Stars. Here’s the video:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UOxkGD8qRB4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>The song features Korean and American singers, who all do an excellent job. The musical style broadly conforms to the EDM end of K-pop, plausibly like something from YG producer <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teddy_Park">Teddy Park</a>, the production powerhouse behind Blackpink’s work.  It’s hard to quantify, but Pop/Stars feels a touch more westernised to me, but there’s enough K for the experience not to feel ersatz.</p>

<p>While musically the song’s well-constructed, and the production is immaculate, there’s not much going on lyrically - unless you’re a connoisseur of bog-standard hiphop “I’m much better than you” braggadocio. But since pop music isn’t supposed to be Milton, I’ll give it a pass. All up then, I reckon Pop/stars is manufactured pop <em>par excellence</em>, and the <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/4gOc8TsQed9eqnqJct2c5v">hundreds of millions of Spotify plays</a> and YouTube views suggests it has been very successful.</p>

<p>What of the video? Well, for me it’s a bravura display of motion, colour, and secondary sex characteristics. (Let me wag my finger at the vid’s appeal to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Male_gaze">male gaze</a>, though. Boo!) It doesn’t put a foot wrong.</p>

<p>One final thing to mention: Pop/stars was performed in a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=p9oDlvOV3qs">bizarre ritual</a> at the opening ceremony of the 2018 League of Legends world champs (presented by Mastercard!), held in (appropriately) Incheon, South Korea. The real singers of the song were present, accompanied virtually by their K/DA avatars. If I’ve got this correct, the virtual members could only be viewed by spectators via an augmented reality app on their smartphones. I have complex feelings about whether this is pioneering or silly, but I will say that if I’d tried to explain the scenario to my late grandfather, he’d have given me a look like I was a fucking idiot.</p>

<h2 id="more">“More”</h2>

<p>In 2020 K/DA released a second single, “More”, which is indeed more of the same:</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3VTkBuxU4yk" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>

<p>Musically I thin More has an edge over Pop/Stars, but the video is greatly inferior. The character design is more 3 dimensional look, but only serves to send the viewer tumbling into the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncanny_valley">uncanny valley</a>, and the result is vaguely repellant. Again there’s not much going on lyrically. So it’s a bit of a mixed bag. Great to listen to, less enjoyable to watch.</p>

<p>In my JoJo survey I jokingly suggested some MMD videos of JJBA characters dancing to More were superior to the original. That’s a bit unfair, but I will say this video of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8l1MBNgXLr4">JoJo villains replicating More’s antics</a> is pleasingly silly.</p>

<p>2020 also saw K/DA release <a href="https://open.spotify.com/artist/4gOc8TsQed9eqnqJct2c5v/discography/all?uri=spotify:album:26IdRjba8f8DNa7c0FwfQb">All Out</a> an EP which featured More plus four other songs. You’d expect the non-single songs to be filler, but they’re actually pretty decent. And all up I find myself hoping that K/DA will release, well, <em>more</em> material in future.</p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>Compared with the K-pop mill, K/DA feels comparatively less exploitative, in that the human vocalists are basically session performers, so outside of recording sessions (and at least one League of Legends stadium appearence), they’re free to live their lives as they want. K/DA may be an overly refined, nutrition-free corporate product, but it’s one I can enjoy without feeling guilty about it. As for genuine K-pop groups, bless them all! I hope you make it out alive.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jojo’s Bizarre Adventure</title><link href="/2022/03/27/jjba.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jojo’s Bizarre Adventure" /><published>2022-03-27T00:00:00+13:00</published><updated>2022-03-27T00:00:00+13:00</updated><id>/2022/03/27/jjba</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/03/27/jjba.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JoJo%27s_Bizarre_Adventure">Jojo’s Bizarre Adventure</a> (henceforth JJBA, or just “JoJo” for a bit of variety) is a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manga">manga</a> penned by one <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hirohiko_Araki">Hirohiko Araki</a>. It began publication in 1987, and is still a going concern today.</p>

<p>I think I first heard of JJBA in 2019, possibly in relation to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Disastrous_Life_of_Saiki_K.">Saiki K</a>, which contains several references to JoJo. The “Bizarre Adventure” part sounded promising, so I googled it. The <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=jojo%27s+bizarre+adventure&amp;sxsrf=APq-WBuJ9jMZfigR8kRNcivrHGNdlvRW4A:1645516822915&amp;source=lnms&amp;tbm=isch&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=2ahUKEwiojM7t65L2AhUPzzgGHSwBCkEQ_AUoAXoECCgQAw&amp;biw=1999&amp;bih=1332&amp;dpr=1">image results</a> revealed vivid, bewildering depictions of innumerable characters in contorted poses, and wearing outlandish costumes in jarring colours. I didn’t know what the hell I was looking at, but I liked it. For the next while, whenever I remembered JJBA’s existance I would repeat this googlage as a sort of ritual, content just to revel in the enigmatic weirdness, rather than learn more.</p>

<p>But in early 2021 the first season of the anime adaptation turned up on Netflix, and I dived in straight away. It turns out JJBA is every bit as weird and fantastical as I’d imagined, to tell you the truth, I’ve become a bit obsessed. I figured I might be able to extirpate my obsession by writing a brief survey of JJBA. So here goes.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/jjba/all-smaller.jpg" alt="Image of the 8 Jojos" title="All the JoJos so far" /></p>

<h2 id="the-essence-of-jojo">The essence of JoJo</h2>

<p>JJBA is split into eight parts, with each part being a mostly self-contained story that features a member of the Joestar bloodline. These protagonists have names containing two “Jo” syllables, so the titular JoJo (of the bizarre adventure) is actually 8 different people. The broad premise of each story is that a JoJo and his or her allies are pitted against a suitably nefarious antagonist and their allies. The first 6 parts are sequential, while parts 7 &amp; 8 are echoes of two of the first six parts, but set in a different universe.</p>

<p>As I understand it (from a cursory glance at Wikipedia), JJBA follows the convention of a “tournament” manga. As you might expect from the name, this genre focuses heavily on antagonists trying best each other, with much of the entertainment coming from:</p>

<ul>
  <li>combatants conducting lengthy internal monologues about strategy</li>
  <li>a lot of trash talk</li>
  <li>twists and turns in the fortunes of war as each antagonist tries to one-up the other with their fighting prowess.</li>
</ul>

<p>If the bare-bones of the tournament genre doesn’t sound that interesting - and note that millions of Western wrestling fans will completely disagree with you - JJBA’s point of difference is to make the confrontations frequently convoluted, weird, and grotesque. So, you know, sign me up!</p>

<h1 id="the-parts">The parts</h1>

<p>In this section I’m going to outline synopses of the existing eight parts to give a flavour of the story.</p>

<p>There’s one final thing to note before we start: it will quickly become apparent to you that Araki routinely gives characters the names of Western pop or rock groups, or the names of their songs. How a particular name lands with you will depend on your appetite for whimsy, or your musical taste. See what you think; we’ll come back to this subject later.</p>

<h2 id="part-1---phantom-blood-1987">Part 1 - Phantom Blood (1987)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jonathan.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Jonathan Joestar and his nemesis Dio Brando" title="Jonathan Joestar and his nemesis Dio Brando" />
    <figcaption>Jonathan Joestar and his nemesis Dio Brando. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The saga kicks off with the adventures of Jonathan Joestar (nicknamed Jojo), an upper crust kid in 1880s England. He’s in conflict with his adoptive brother <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ronnie_James_Dio">Dio</a> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marlon_Brando">Brando</a>, a ne’er do well orphan with designs on the Joestar fortune. All is relatively mundane at first (give or take a barbecued dog) until Jonathan cottons on to Dio’s nefariority complex. In desperation, Dio dons the family Aztec stone mask, and is handily transformed into a vampire. Though built like a brick shithouse, Jonathan needs a supernatural power up in order to contend with Dio. Lucky then that upon realising this, he immediately meets Will A. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Led_Zeppelin">Zeppeli</a>, a flamboyant Italian practitioner of the art of “hamon” (“ripple” in Japanese), the energy of the sun that a practitioner gains - somehow - through breathing a certain way. The chief value of hamon energy is that it is deadly to vampires.</p>

<p>With the aid of Zeppelli and cockney chum <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/REO_Speedwagon">Robert E.O. Speedwagon</a> (geddit??), JoJo confronts Dio and his zombie horde. Who will be victorious?</p>

<p>So I’ll grant you that all of that sounds like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_load_of_old_cobblers">cobblers</a>, but I find it to be absolutely <em>my</em> kind of cobblers. Nothing is done by halves: Dio is an utterly scurrilous villain, while Jonathan embodies chivalric English gentlemanliness to the point of tedium. (Indeed, Araki decided to move on to a new JoJo storyline because he found Jonathan too boring.) If our protagonist and antagonist are unremarkably good vs evil, there are plenty of lurid incidental details to keep the reader or viewer engaged. My favourite is when, Jonathan and his chums are ambushed by zombie Jack the Ripper erupting out of the body of a horse. Meanwhile, in classic manga style, combatants announce their special moves as they perform them; Jonathan’s being the rousing (if dish-washing liquid reminiscent) “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3KGHViJqTsk&amp;t=38s">SUNLIGHT YELLOW OVERDRIVE</a>!”</p>

<p>Phantom Blood is a somewhat flawed prototype for the larger JoJo saga: its charm being strictly of the “so weird it’s good” variety. Many readers skip the part altogether to get to the better stuff. I think doing this would be a shame; for all its faults Phantom Blood is always engagingly silly, and would I’d recommend it to anyone who loves campy heroic (and gory) action.</p>

<p>This is spoilers, but it’s sort of necessary to explain the whole saga: after only a few months of writing Phantom Blood, Araki decided to ditch Jonathan by killing him off. This was done in a typically understated fashion (I’m kidding of course; it’s ridiculous!). Having a protagonist snuff it was unheard of in late 80’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sh%C5%8Dnen_manga">shonen manga</a>, so Araki was taking quite a gamble with his readers. Happily, though, the experiment paid off, and the stage was set for decades of periodic JoJo reinvention.</p>

<h2 id="part-2---battle-tendency-1987---1989">Part 2 - Battle Tendency (1987 - 1989)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/joseph.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Joseph Joestar" title="Joseph Joestar" />
    <figcaption>Joseph Joestar. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>JJBA’s second chapter is the aptly-named Battle Tendency, a globe-trotting Indiana Jonesy adventure set in the late 1930s. The new JoJo is Jonathan’s grandson Joseph, a 19 year old unchivalrous, wise-cracking goof prone to running away when the chips are down (a practice he refers to as his “ultimate technique”). In essence he’s the anti Jonathan.</p>

<p>Extending the stone mask backstory, Joseph is pitted against Kars, Whammu, and Eisidesi (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cars">Cars</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wham!">Wham</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AC/DC">AC/DC</a>, naturally), the reanimated Aztec superbeing vampires collectively known as the Pillar Men. Aiding Joseph in this conflict are his frenemy Caesar Zeppeli (grandson of Will. A), the enigmatic Hamon instructor Lisa Lisa, and Rudol[sic] von Stroheim, a… well, there’s no pussyfooting around it: he’s a Nazi. (I concede this detail is a bit “problematic”, but the tone is so absurd - esp when von Stroheim becomes a cyborg with a cannon in his chest - that it seems churlish to take it seriously.)</p>

<p>The plot involves the Pillar Men being awakened from thousands of years of slumber by those pesky Nazis. Joseph hastily trains up in Hamon master (mostly off-screen), and then works to protect the Stone of Aja (a glowing ruby manga macguffin) and generally thwart the Pillar Men’s plan to become “ultimate lifeforms”. The subdued climax of the part involves Joseph and Kars battling it out on a chunk of rock recently ejected into space by an erupting volcano.</p>

<p>Battle Tendency is a rollicking adventure that marks a significant improvement on Phantom Blood’s schlock and awe. It’s not a perfect story by any means, but Araki’s story-telling is becoming more assured.</p>

<h2 id="part-3---stardust-crusaders-1989---1992">Part 3 - Stardust Crusaders (1989 - 1992)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jotaro.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Jotaro Kujo with his stand STAR PLATINUM" title="Jotaro Kujo with his stand STAR PLATINUM" />
    <figcaption>Jotaro Kujo with his stand STAR PLATINUM. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The third JoJo outing featured some significant tweaks to the format. Bored of taking his protagonists through the plot mechanics of learning the Hamon technique, Araki invented the concept of “stands”, Hamon spirits controlled by a human user. Each stand has a unique set of reality warping qualities that can be utilised in battle. Because stands are an emergent property of their user’s personality, they come fully formed without the need of training to manifest and use them.</p>

<p>To get a better idea of how stands work you could watch a JJBA anime battle clip on YouTube, but the link I’ll toss in here is some <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b_g9ufxg28k">game play</a> from the entirely understated 1998 JJBA arcade game (made by the creators of Street Fighter!).</p>

<p>A further innovation with Stardust Crusaders was to leave behind the stone mask Aztec vampire “mythos” element from the saga. There is one nod to the earlier parts: the return of Dio!</p>

<p>The story: it is the late 1980s. Dio has returned after spending a century in a coffin at the bottom of the Atlantic. Worse still, he’s managed to cobble his head onto the body of Jonathan Joestar (don’t think about it too much). Additionally, his name apparently gets stuck in capslock, for he’s henceforth known as DIO. With the help of witch <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enya">Enya</a> the Hag, Dio acquires a stand. And because Jonathan’s body is involved, Jonathan’s descendants (Joseph Joestar, Joseph’s daughter Holly, and her half-Japanase son Jotaro Kujo) also acquire stands. Okay then…</p>

<p>An ageing but admirably buff Joseph Joestar visits Jotaro and Holly in Japan and helps Jotaro to control his stand’s destructive and kleptomaniac tendencies. (Said stand is named STAR PLATINUM. I’ll henceforth refer to stands in caps as well, because stand users tend to portentously announce their names when deploying them, and ALL CAPS conveys the majesty of this better). Soon after, Holly falls ill because her stand is too powerful for her delicate feminine nature (apparently), and in order to save her Joseph and Jotaro must kill DIO within 50 days!</p>

<p>With this ticking clock in place, the Joestars (aided by comrades Avdol, Kakyoin, Polnareff, and later Iggy) journey to DIO’s lair in Egypt. Along the way they are ambushed by a what feels like an unending number of stand users allied to DIO. Eventually they reach Cairo and the final battle pits DIO and Jotaro <em>stando a stando</em>.</p>

<p>Stardust Crusaders was the story that boosted JJBA to wider cultural awareness in Japan, making Jotaro <em>the</em> JoJo. Dressed like a delinquent Japanese school boy, albeit one with a 30 year old’s body, Jotaro certainly looks the part. Araki based Jotaro’s demeanour on Clint Eastwood’s Dirty Harry, so he’s basically a stoic, callous, antihero grump who glowers at his surroundings with the dead eyes of a bird of prey. But all this is window-dressing; what makes Jotaro truly a rebel is that he’s frequently rude to his mum. (This must be truly thrilling to Japanese readers…)</p>

<p>I think Jotaro’s character design is perhaps Araki’s best, and he deserves his iconic status. That said, his surly nature makes him unsuitable for handling the story’s comic moments - of which there are many - so much of Stardust Crusaders’ narrative focus is given to the comical Polnareff, and the reliably entertaining Joseph Joestar. This decoupling of the narrative from the protagonist would become more prevalent in subsequent parts.</p>

<p>Despite the iconic status of Jotaro and his gang, much of Stardust Crusaders’ structure is episodic and repetitive. Over and over again Team JoJo will arrive at a new location, a stand will attack them, and the stand’s owner has to be identified, confronted, and defeated. The group moves on. Repeat. It’s not all bad: there are plenty of memorable moments in these episodes. But they sort of blur together for readers, making for a fairly significant architectural flaw.</p>

<h2 id="part-4---diamond-is-unbreakable-1992---1995">Part 4 - Diamond is Unbreakable (1992 - 1995)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/diu.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of the main Diamond is Unbreakable gang" title="The main Diamond is Unbreakable gang" />
    <figcaption>The main Diamond is Unbreakable gang. Clockwise from left: Okuyasu Nijimura, Josuke Higashikata, Jotaro Kujo, Koichi Hirose, Rohan Kishibe. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In a marked departure from the epic settings of the previous three parts, Diamond is Unbreakable (Diamond is Unbreakable)’s story is confined to the fictional Japanese seaside town of Morioh. Araki made another tweak to the broader JJBA “lore”: in Stardust Crusaders, the origin of stand abilities was left unexplained, but in Diamond is Unbreakable “standiness” is conveyed upon a person when they are pierced by a magical arrow.</p>

<p>The story: it’s the far off future of 1999, and our new JoJo is schoolboy Josuke Hishigata, the illegitimate son of Joseph Joestar. Joseph himself is now elderly and frail, so Jotaro is saddled with handling the exposition, and he isn’t happy about it. Josuke’s has a DIO-inherited stand called CRAZY DIAMOND, which has the somewhat paradoxical qualities of being able to both inflict immense violence and to heal people. (From a narrative perspective, CRAZY DIAMOND allows Araki his heroes to suffer terrible injuries and still survive. There are moments in Diamond is Unbreakable that might make you wince.)</p>

<p>The initial arc of the story sees Jotaro coming to town to protect Josuke from a stand-wielding killer. It transpires that an additional, unknown agent is going about Morioh spiking residents with a stand arrow to create a diverse array of new antagonists and allies. Once Josuke and his stand-wielding schoolfriends (Jotaro remains present but on the sidelines) have dealt with this initial swarm of villains, the central big bad of the story appears. Kira Yoshikage is a seemingly mild-mannered (if strikingly Bowie-esque) fellow who has been unobtrusively killing women in Morioh for years (with help from his sinister stand, KILLER QUEEN). Learning of Kira’s existence, Josuke and his gang set about tracking him down. Kira is careful and cunning, but how long can he stay ahead of his pursuers, and what will he do when he is finally unmasked?</p>

<p>While the preceding synopsis is greatly simplified, it demonstrates how Araki’s storytelling has become more sophisticated since Phantom Blood. But the true joy of Diamond is Unbreakable is the wealth of characters and detail Araki uses to populate Morioh. (Indeed, Araki fell in love with Morioh so much that he returned there in part 8.)</p>

<p>If Jotaro was at times slightly sidelined as the main character in Stardust Crusaders, Josuke is even more so in Diamond is Unbreakable. But this time it’s less from necessity, and more because Araki wants to explore the lives of the denizens of Morioh. In particular, much coverage is given to the travails of Josuke’s diminuitive friend Koichi, and, later in the story, the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Manga_artist">mangaka</a> Rohan Kishibe.</p>

<p>Despite this narrative de-emphasis, Josuke is still a fleshed out character (moreso than the one-note Jotaro). In fact in some ways Josuke is the most grounded of all the JoJos. While he is imbued with typical Joestar heroism, he’s also very much a high school kid: he comes up with (very dubious) schemes for making money, and makes some questionable choices. His relationship with his estranged father Joseph is also nuanced. Eventually they’re sort of reconciled, but there’s never a sense of happily ever after. In fact the biggest satisfaction Josuke gets from the relationship is when he manages to steal Joseph’s wallet.</p>

<p>If Josuke is the most down-to-Earth JoJo, Kira is the most relatable villain. While the portrayal is hardly sympathetic, we do have opportunity to see inside Kira’s and understand him a bit better. Much time is given to Kira’s nightmarish experiences trying to evade detection and resume his quiet life.</p>

<p>It’s also worth mentioning that despite its relatively down-to-earth setting, Diamond is Unbreakable still manages to serve up the sort of sublime nonsense for which JJBA is famed. There’s the chap who is trapped inside his stand, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superfly_(song)">SUPER FLY</a>, which manifests in the physical form of an electricity pylon. There’s the appearance of an apparent extraterrestrial, <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Mikitaka_Hazekura">Mikitaka Hazekura</a>, whose shapeshifting abilities are co-opted by Josuke to best Rohan at gambling. Most brain-cracking of all is when the ghost of Kira’s father, Yoshihiro Kira, entered the story. You see Yoshihiro gets trapped by Jotaro in a polaroid photo taken by Yoshihiro’s stand, a supernatural camera called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atom_Heart_Mother">ATOM HEART FATHER</a>. Yoshishiro manages to grab the stand arrow, and escapes when his photographic domicile gets blown away on the wind. He then goes on an arrow spiking spree in order to create new stand users that he persuades to fight Josuke and co. I cite this as an example of how the JoJo crazy can get very convoluted.</p>

<p>All up, Diamond is Unbreakable is the best JJBA story the anime has covered. In terms of quality, and with its small town vibe and psychedelic whimsy, Diamond is Unbreakable feels a bit like Araki’s equivalent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sgt._Pepper%27s_Lonely_Hearts_Club_Band">Sgt. Pepper’s Lonely Hearts Club Band</a> (a comparison I think he might appreciate).</p>

<h2 id="part-5---golden-wind-1995---1999">Part 5 - Golden Wind 1995 - 1999</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/giorno.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Giorno Giovanna" title="Giorno Giovanna" />
    <figcaption>Giorno Giovanna. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>For the next JoJo adventure we travel from Morioh in 1999 to Italy in 2001. But first, a detour back to the mid 80s! While in Cairo waiting for the Stardust Crusaders to show up, DIO impregnated a Japanese woman, and the resulting issue was the suspiciously blond Giorno Giovanni. Now, you’ll recall that DIO ended up being a vampire’s head on Jonathan Joestar’s body, so Giorno is actually Jonathan’s son, and therefore a JoJo (or in this case, GioGio!). Even so, however, Giorno has DIOish blond hair, and shares DIO’s battle cry of “Muda muda muda!” (“useless useless useless!”). So is Giorno a goodie or a baddie?</p>

<p>On to the story, set in the year 2001. Jotaro learns of Giorno’s existence, and dispatches poor little Koichi to Naples to ascertain if Giorno is good or evil. After getting off on the wrong foot with Giorno, Koichi eventually determines that Giorno is benign, and promptly exits the story to allow Giorno to take centre stage.</p>

<p>As a Joestar, Giorno is automatically entitled to a stand, and his is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Gold_Experience">GOLD EXPERIENCE</a>. It comes with the power to transmute objects into living matter (small animals, plants, etc), making him, like Josuke, both a dealer of damage and a medic.</p>

<p>At the start of the story Giorno is a petty Neapolitan thief, but he, Giorno, has a dream: to break up the drug-dealing mafia gang known as “Passione”, by taking out its enigmatic Boss.</p>

<p>Giorno has a run in with junior mafioso Bruno Bucciarati (stand: STICKY FINGERS; haircut: bowl) and their battle goes so well that not only does Giorno win, but he manages to co-opt Bucchiarati to his cause. Giorno joins Bucciarati’s mafia unit, La Squadra. Soon after the gang get assigned to protect the Boss’s daughter Trish (eventual stand: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spice_Girls">SPICE GIRL</a>). Bucciaratti delivers Trish to the Boss, but trouble breaks out, and the gang is forced to go on the run with all of Passione hunting them. The final confrontation occurs in the Colisseum (previously visited in part 2). Passione’s Boss is revealed to be the dastardly Diavolo (Italian for the devil, geddit!), whose fearsome stand <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Crimson">KING CRIMSON</a> can undo the causation of events affecting him. Who will prevail??</p>

<p>Golden Wind is Araki’s homage to both Italy and mafia dramas. 15-year old Giorno is modelled on Michelangelo’s David (if David wore a braided ponytail and sported three pastry rolls on his forehead). The story can be summed up as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goodfellas">Goodfellas</a> with stands, which at face value is a winning premise.</p>

<p>Sadly Golden Wind turns out to be the weakest of the JoJo parts I’ve consumed so far. There are two critical flaws. The first is that Giorno’s character is very flat. He’s not got Joseph’s chutzpah, Jotaro’s flintiness, or Josuke’s charm. Even Jonathan Joestar has more personality. In fact Giorno is overshadowed in his own story by La Squadra’s other members, especially Bucciarati. In fact even standard-issue, damsel-in-distress Trish gets more development.</p>

<p>The second problem is that the climax of Golden Wind is muddled and confusing. It’s ok for a reader to be slightly baffled at a JoJo ending, but you should be grinning with delight at the weirdness, not frowning because you have no idea what’s going on.</p>

<p>Golden Wind’s narrative may have some flaws, but the situation is not all bad. The character designs are some of Araki’s most out-there creations, the stand fights are some of the most compelling in all of JJBA, and Diavolo is another interesting villain. Nevertheless it’s notable that while each part in the series up to this one had improved on the last, Golden Wind marks the first dip in quality.</p>

<p>To sum up, I would say that if Diamond is Unbreakable was Araki’s Sgt. Pepper, Golden Wind is very much his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles_(album)">White Album</a>. But I feel obliged to point out that Golden Wind is very popular among Western fans of JJBA, so my opinion may be very much in the minority.</p>

<h2 id="part-6---stone-ocean-1999---2003">Part 6 - Stone Ocean (1999 - 2003)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jolyne.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Jolyne Kujo" title="Jolyne Cujo" />
    <figcaption>Jolyne Cujo. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Until part 6, JJBA’s female characters were few in number and seldom well-realised. Part 1’s Erina was girlfriend-by-numbers, and though part 2’s Lisa Lisa was cast as a badass femme fatale, she didn’t rise much beyond noir cliche, and she endured a few demeaning moments. As for Stardust Crusaders, it was largely female free, aside from Jotaro’s feeble mother Holly and the wicked crone Enyaba. Diamond is Unbreakable did have more female characters: the frighteningly possessive Yukako Yamagishi and ghost girl Reimi Sugimoto being the most prominent. Again, though, their roles were more peripheral to the frankly sausage-heavy core cast.</p>

<p>It’s true that shonen comics tend to be very masculine in their focus, but Araki’s career has been about transcending manga cliches in interesting ways, and he was clearly capable of better. With Stone Ocean he finally delivered, giving us our first lady JoJo, Jolyne Kujo. Araki further intensified the female focus by setting the story primarily in the women’s wing of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/On_Green_Dolphin_Street_(song)">Green Dolphin Street</a> prison, providing Jolyne with some female sidekicks. I should be careful here: strictly speaking one sidekick is a colony of zooplankton (pronouns unknown), but they(?) “pass” as female. (I’m down with this identity crap, mother fuckers…)</p>

<p>The premise: it’s 2011 and Jolyne Kujo is framed for a crime she didn’t commit! When sentenced to many years in prison, her estranged daddy Jotaro helps out as only he can: by giving her part of a stand arrow so that she may accidentally pierce herself with it and thereby obtain a stand. Once in possession of her stand, STONE FREE, Jolyne can protect herself in prison. After Jotaro is left grievously injured in a prison visit gone very wrong, Jolyne is faced with needing to save her father, unmask the secret villain behind the assassination attempt, and escape from Green Dolphin Street Prison.</p>

<p>This initial premise promises none of the mucking around that marred Golden Wind. However the narrative quickly descends into a bunch of pointless stand battles to kind of pad things out. The climax, when it comes, however is spectacular and of truly cosmic import, concluding the wider Joestar saga. Is it good? Well, Araki had a vision, and by golly he sees it through. I respect it, but in my hard of hearts it feels anticlimactic to me.</p>

<h2 id="part-7---steel-ball-run-2005---2011">Part 7 - Steel Ball Run (2005 - 2011)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/johnny.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Gyro Zeppeli and Johnny Joestar" title="Gyro Zeppeli and Johnny Joestar" />
    <figcaption>Gyro Zeppeli and Johnny Joestar. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>After Stone Ocean Araki reset the narrative timeline, and Parts 7 and 8 occur in a different universe. Steel Ball Run is a retelling of Jonathan Joestar’s story, except with the premise scrambled.</p>

<p>We’re back in the 19th century (1890) and Johnny Joestar is a paraplegic jockey understandably down on his luck. He meets Gyro Zeppeli (this part’s Will. A. Zeppeli), who possesses mysterious spin power over his “steel balls” (literally, this isn’t a euphemism…) which Johnny believes can cure his paraplegia. Johnny tags along with Gyro in a horse race across the USA called the Steel Ball Run (which is presumably a reference to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Burt_Reynolds">Burt Reynolds</a> “classic” <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Cannonball_Run">The Cannonball Run</a>).</p>

<p>At time of writing there is no anime adaptation, but I found the premise so intriguing I “obtained” the manga and consumed it. It’s pretty good, though a little overlong, packing in just a few too many inscrutable stand confrontations. Visually it’s very impressive, however, and I find the flair of the designs for Johnny and Gyro in particular to be among the best Araki has produced. Johnny sports a sky blue jockey silks and a horseshoe-emblazoned cap, looking somewhere between a gypsy fortune teller and a 1930s Hollywood starlet. Gyro, the androgynous caped cowboy with coolishly impractical goggles and hat is, well, pretty awesome!</p>

<p>It’s worth pausing a moment to ponder Araki’s decision to reboot the saga. Normally when this happens in a comic (see endless Batman/Superman/Spiderman reboots) it’s a sign the story running out of creative steam. Reboots are also dangerous generally because they dilute the original story by making it a bit whatever you want it to be. Seldom a good look.</p>

<p>So SBR could be seen as that, but I think the impetus for the reboot is as simple as Araki wanting to set his next JoJo story in the Wild West, and setting it outside the existing JJBA continuity would be the most plausible way to achieve this. Additionally it appears Johnny is only a very loose analogue of Jonathan, so it’s not so much an alternative past as a completely new story. In short, I think the SBR reboot is a reasonable way to keep telling more JoJo stories.</p>

<h2 id="part-8---jojolion-2011---2021">Part 8 - Jojolion (2011 - 2021)</h2>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jojolion.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of Josuke Higashikata and Yasuho Hirose" title="Josuke Higashikata and Yasuho Hirose" />
    <figcaption>Josuke Higashikata and Yasuho Hirose. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Jojolion is the SBR universe equivalent of Diamond is Unbreakable. I know even less about Jojolion than SBR. The protagonist, who is also called Josuke Higishigata as in Diamond is Unbreakable, wears a sailor suit and trainers. Sadly, his stand is not called New York, New York…</p>

<p>Once again the look is amazing. And that’s all I can say of the story until it gets an anime adaptation in approximately four years.</p>

<p>SBR posed the question “why reboot?”; Jojolion makes me wonder “why return to Morioh?”, especially if the first time round is the high point of the manga. It would be justified if the story Araki wanted to tell is a good one, but if not, Jojolion is just a creative retread.</p>

<h2 id="part-9---jojolands">Part 9 - Jojolands?</h2>

<p>After more than a year’s break after the conclusion of Jojolion, the next part is Jojolands, kicking off in Feb 2023. At time of writing, this is next month. We’ll see what happens.</p>

<h2 id="thus-spoke-kishibe-rohan">Thus Spoke Kishibe Rohan</h2>

<p>Araki’s first JoJo spinoff was Thus Spoke Kishibe Rohan, an anthology horror series involving the mangaka character (and author insert) from Diamond is Unbreakable. A short series animating four of those stories is available on Netflix. What could be a largely disposable folly is redeemed by Araki’s highly developed sense of the macabre. Indeed the tales feel like Japanese ghost stories (even when set in Europe). One curious side-effect of these stories is that they provides the JoJo-uninitiated with an easy entry point to the JoJo style, without having to endure the silliness of the first episode of Phantom Blood or the backstory-heavy beginnings to later parts. That’s my recommendation, anyway.</p>

<h2 id="the-future">The future</h2>

<p>The meme that <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ShitPostCrusaders/comments/f483qj/araki_the_vampire_this_man_just_doesnt_want_to_age/">Araki is immortal</a> notwithstanding, the great man is in his 60s now, and given Jojolion took 10 years to complete, part 9 may well be the last JJBA part before he retires.  Alterntatively, in recent years Araki has handed out the keys to other mangaka to produce spinoff JoJo stories, and this suggests the possibility of a post-Araki life for JJBA. Would that life be interesting without Araki’s genius? I would say almost certainly not, but a mangaka of similar talent could make a good go of it.</p>

<h1 id="discussion">Discussion</h1>

<p>Now you have a bit of a handle on the story, I’m going to make some commentary on the JoJo phenomenon. It’s going to be a bit scattershot, but will hopefully provide the reader with some entertainment.</p>

<h2 id="the-anime">The anime</h2>

<p>The anime adaptation by David Productions has been pretty good so far. Seasons 1-3 (covering parts 1 - 4) had a sense of assuredness and confidence, and a commitment to not only depict but also celebrate JJBA. As will be apparent with the lengthy music discussion below, a lot of effort was put into the score.</p>

<p>At times the faithfulness of the adaptation is almost a detriment to the animation. The pacing of season 1, featuring two parts in 26 episodes, is brisk and lively compared to the interminable slog of the 48 episodes of season 2 (the entirety of Stardust Crusaders). While seasons 3 and 4 (Diamond is Unbreakable and Golden Wind) were pared back to 39 episodes apiece, these seasons too are bit mushier (in my mind at least) than season 1.</p>

<p>It’s hard to say exactly why, but seasons 4 and 5 (parts 5 and 6) don’t have quite the same shine as earlier seasons - the style of JoJo feels de-emphasised. I wonder if budgets for more recent seasons have been cut. Certainly Covid must have affected the production of season 5. (Interestingly the recent JJBA spinoff episode OVA Thus Spoke Kishibe Rohan <em>does</em> feel more styley.) Style is a bit hard to quantify, and I have to say I’m not sure I can disentangle this impression with the fact that I’ve found the stories of parts 5 and 6 less enjoyable than those of earlier parts.</p>

<h2 id="arakis-visual-style">Araki’s visual style</h2>

<p>Araki is very much into fashion and art, in particular Italian Renaissance art (which may explain the almost sculptural visual sensibility of JJBA - or to put it more plainly, all that <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/jojos-pose">JoJo posing</a>).</p>

<p>The art style of JJBA has consistently evolved since 1987. Phantom Blood and Battle Tendency weren’t too visually <em>oeutre</em>,  at least compared to later works, though Araki provided highly baroque covers for the JJBA manga volumes of the time, which hinted at a desire to bust out some crazy. The character designs in Stardust Crusaders were much more distinctive, and a further quantum shift happened with Diamond is Unbreakable. The musclebound physiques of the early JoJo parts slimmed down considerably, and the facial designs became more stylised.</p>

<p>Araki went to an extreme of outlandishness with Golden Wind, before reining it in somewhat with Stone Ocean. Steel Ball Run saw a move to a softer, more austere style, especially with characters’ faces. In fact you could argue that since 2005 every character in JJBA has had the same face: blank eyes, lips pouting, expressionless and seemingly unknowable. Goodies and baddies alike could appear on a Vogue cover. These stares have a feel of otherworldly contemplation, if you want to state it charitably; but there’s also a dehumanising quality, like looking at a collection of automatons.</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jojolion5.jpg" width="300" alt="Picture of the Jojolion gang" title="The Jojolion gang" />
    <figcaption>The Jojolion gang. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>And yet the effect of the art remains beguiling and intriguing, so I’m a bit torn. It would be interesting to see where (if it all) Araki’s style might evolve next.</p>

<h1 id="music">Music</h1>

<p>I’m going to ramble about a series of music-related topics with which JJBA intersects.</p>

<h2 id="musical-character-names">Musical character names</h2>

<p>As mentioned earlier, Araki habitually names characters (or their stands) after Western rock groups, and more often than not the effect of this - for me at least - is both jarring and amusing. One early example: Jonathan Joestar and friends get confronted by a reanimated medieval knight named Bruford (“Bluford”, technically, see Localisation below). Now “Bruford” is an English name, but if you’re already aware of names like “Speedwagon” and “Dio”, you’ll conclude that it’s a reference to Bill Bruford, drummer of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King_Crimson">King Crimson</a>.</p>

<p>Araki’s musical taste is apparently very eclectic, with JJBA characters or stands named after musical acts as disparate as <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Mariah">Mariah Carey</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steely_Dan">Steely Dan</a>, <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Straizo">Dire Straits</a>, the <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Sex_Pistols">Sex Pistols</a>, and <a href="https://jojo.fandom.com/wiki/Smokey_Brown">Smokey Robinson</a>. Some names suggest impeccable taste, while others are kind of laughable: Stardust Crusaders’ penultimate antagonist is a formidable opponent underwhelmingly named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vanilla_Ice">Vanilla Ice</a>. (Though the situation is somewhat redeemed by said antagonist’s stand being called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cream_(band)">CREAM</a>.)</p>

<p>What is the meaning of all this?! On the one hand this naming convention feels arbitrary, like Araki just went through an encyclopaedia of rock and used names at random. I have no reason to believe that he actually did this, but the effect is largely the same.</p>

<p>Quibbles aside, Araki’s musical naming convention is at least kind of fun when he names stands after <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Kraft_Work">bands I like at least</a>. And he does manage to make the Queen song <a href="https://jojowiki.com/Killer_Queen">Killer Queen</a> sinister, which is quite an achievement. That said, I’m disappointed there’s no ABBA or BEEGEES. Perhaps something for part 9?</p>

<h3 id="localisation">Localisation</h3>

<p>The strangeness of Araki’s musical naming convention is taken to a higher power via the practice of “localisation”, where the English translation of a manga/anime name referring to real world entities are “subtly” renamed, in an effort to avoid copyright problems. The renaming can be as simple as using the Japanese transliteration of the non-Japanese name. For example, Wham becomes “Wammu”. But at other times, an alternative name is used. For example, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlos_Santana">Santana</a>, a character in Battle Tendency, is renamed “San Viento” in the manga/anime. Jolyne’s stand STONE FREE is renamed Stone Ocean.</p>

<p>But sometimes the results of localisation changes are unintentionally funny. One that sticks in my head (because the change is almost antithetical to the original) is the stand named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kraftwerk">KRAFTWORK</a>, which gets localised to “Arts and Crafts”. The most humorously awful localisation change, by quite some margin, is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Deeds_Done_Dirt_Cheap">DIRTY DEEDS DONE DIRT CHEAP</a> (a moniker given to a Steel Ball Run stand), which localisation mutates to “Filthy acts, at a reasonable price”.</p>

<h2 id="the-anime-soundtracks">The Anime soundtracks</h2>

<h3 id="original-music">Original music</h3>

<p>The chief joy of the Phantom Blood arc of the anime’s first season is opening theme “<a href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=R2Be4YJTORw">Sono Chi no Sadame</a>”, a rollicking piece of theatrical rock, featuring some fearsome tenor bellowing. The song feels very old fashioned, going not just back to JJBA’s 80s’s origins, but earlier still. If it was a western production I’d say the song’s over the top tone was intended to be tongue in cheek, but I’m not sure if that’s the actually the case here. In any event: hell of a song.</p>

<p>Battle Tendency’s soundtrack was composed by Taku Iwasaki and features some EDM numbers like “Welcome to the World” and “Overdrive”, as well as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qawwali">Qawwali</a> dubstep of fan-favourite <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bNJmVJwkJwk">“Awake”</a>. The opening theme for the part is the unpleasantly-named but otherwise genial “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PcuTPjgMiXw">Bloody Stream</a>” which complements the irreverant tone of Battle Tendency very nicely.</p>

<p>The score for subsequent seasons of JJBA (so far at least) have been composed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yugo_Kanno">Yugo Kanno</a>. I think it’s fair to say that Kanno has made JoJo soundtracks definitively his own. Supremely eclectic, his musical style can be roughly described as “everything”. The musical recipe: take elements of metal, hiphop, and dubstep, and then drop a jazz orchestra on top of them. While the catchy “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EP62gl-sj2I">Golden Wind</a>” has taken on a life of its own in TikTok memes, I think Kanno’s triumph is the uneasy <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9yGGNohmAT0">Kira’s theme</a> from Part 4.</p>

<p>The last original soundtrack pieces I want to highlight are the first and third opening songs for Diamond is Unbreakable. The first, “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=20m00ohYASw">Crazy, Noisy, Bizarre Town</a>”, is a charmingly enthusiastic J disco sort of song. In something of a contrast, “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7VeYP98UT-g">Great Days</a>” is a kind of psychedelic soul number. These songs tell us all we need to know about Diamond is Unbreakable’s contrast in style to earlier parts. In fact you couldn’t come up with a greater contrast to the wonderfully hyper macho opening themes for Stardust Crusaders (“<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eLwuQwKs4yA">Stand Proud</a>” and “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mNJBDHvznWs">End of the World</a>”, which, by the way, are also great).</p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/jojo-montage.jpg" alt="Montage of stills from JJBA anime opening" title="Montage of graphics from Diamond is Unbreakable anime 'Great Days' opening" />
    <figcaption>Montage of graphics from Diamond is Unbreakable anime "Great Days" opening</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>To my mind the opening songs for Golden Wind and Stone Ocean aren’t quite as strong as earlier seasons, but that’s perhaps because I find their styles less engaging.</p>

<h3 id="end-credit-songs">End credit songs</h3>

<p>I’ve read somewhere (not sure where) that Araki personally chose the music for the end credits of each of the JJBA series. Phantom Blood and Battle Tendency used <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cUyTmUwEUy8">Roundabout</a> by Yes. Although I’m not a Yes novice I confess I wasn’t familiar with the song, and initially assumed that it was by some sort of contemporary Japanese prog rock band. (Well, it’s not implausible!) The frenetic energy of Roundabout is an excellent choice though, especially with the unsettling visuals of channels of blood flowing from Aztec sacrifices - yikes! Amusingly, the episode-end “To Be Continued” motif (inherited from the manga) combined with Roundabout became a <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/yes-roundabout-to-be-continued">meme</a> for numerous internet videos in the mid-2010s.</p>

<p>For the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wV_CwCTOOMI">end titles of the first half of Stardust Crusaders</a> Araki chose the Bangles’ <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walk_Like_an_Egyptian">Walk Like an Egyptian</a>. I hadn’t thought about that song for more than 30 years, but I was elated at how perfectly it fit with the Crusaders’ Egyptian destination, and the surreal whimsy of JJBA generally. In keeping with the in-joke that <a href="https://www.quora.com/Who-is-JoJo-and-why-is-everything-a-reference-to-him">Everything is a JoJo reference</a>, it now almost feels to me like the song was written for JJBA.</p>

<p>For the second half of Stardust Crusaders, the credits featured Last Train Home by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pat_Metheny_Group">Pat Methany Group</a>. This “smooth” jazz fusion piece might seem like an odd choice for Stardust Crusaders, but the result feels oddly poignant, esp when casualties start to mount at the end of the story.</p>

<p>For Diamond is Unbreakable, Araki chose I Need You by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Savage_Garden">Savage Garden</a>. I remember gritting my teeth at that song when it came out, but I tell you what, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dxrrx_XRlyw">against the dayglow pop-art style of Diamond is Unbreakable</a>, the song works brilliantly.</p>

<p>Sadly, my approval of Araki’s choices plummets with the end credits songs for Golden Wind and Stone Ocean. Whether you agree or not depends on how you feel about the following:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Part</th>
      <th>Song</th>
      <th>Artist</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Golden Wind</td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freek%27n_You">Freek’n You</a></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jodeci">Jodeci</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Golden Wind</td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Screen_Behind_the_Mirror">Modern Crusaders</a></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enigma_(German_band)">Enigma</a></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stone Ocean</td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rockferry">Distant Dreamer</a></td>
      <td><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duffy_(singer)">Duffy</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It’s probably a function of my age, but for me these songs have next to no resonance.</p>

<h1 id="the-infinite-jojo-meme-factory">The infinite JoJo meme factory</h1>

<p>If the musical facets of JJBA are a bit of a tangle, the memery Araki’s work inspires is so convoluted not even a topologist could make sense of it. The surreal imagery and hard-boiled dialogue of the manganime is tailor-made out-of-context gifs. There’s rather too many examples to catalogue exhaustively, so I’ll content myself with listing a few examples of which I am very fond.</p>

<h2 id="mmd-vids">MMD vids</h2>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MikuMikuDance">MikuMikuDance</a> is a piece of Japanese software that allows users to animate characters in a 3d space. Unsurprisingly there are JJBA character models available, and YouTube is home to innumerable MMD vids featuring JoJo characters dancing to various songs (lots of different kinds of songs, but K-pop features a lot). The first one I saw was <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WkZKoc0EwEU">straightforward, and oddly elegaic</a>, but there are some that are <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tL1qlNtdVy4">very silly</a>, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8l1MBNgXLr4">one</a> or <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sHvLXNngV4w">two</a> that are arguably better than the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3VTkBuxU4yk">videos they’re based on</a>.</p>

<p>There’s obviously much enjoyment to be had watching a bunch of implausible manga characters dancing with impossible synchrony (well, synchrony impossible outside of North Korea, anyway). But to my mind the MMD JoJo videos truly come into their own when they <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bNJmVJwkJwk">go off-piste</a>. Perhaps the finest examples of this is a trilogy of MMD “skits” that condense the first three JoJo parts into a few minutes:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sPYoyg4Ozrc">phantom_blood.mp4</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pYWfyV6jD3g">battle_tendency.mp4</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qv8TbnZFa3s">stardust_crusaders.mp4</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="other-amusing-youtube-jojo-appearences">Other amusing YouTube JoJo appearences</h2>

<p>Youtube (and doubtless other places too, but I’m too old to use them) has dense thickets of JoJo parodies. Some are very well animated, like this <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CgshWn6edn8">reverent yet slightly too arch example</a>. Then there’s this series mashing up JJBA and Pokemon:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OESzV-MGHYM">Part 1</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=V718G75BH4A">Part 2</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YYa0AgJ85xY">Part 3</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Notes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If JJBA and Pokemon seem to integrate rather too seamlessly, it’s because Pokemon’s concept - opponents battling using proxy supernatural organisms - is very similar to JJBA’s stands. JJBA predates Pokemon by a number of years, but I don’t know whether there has any direct “cross-polination of ideas”.</li>
  <li>These examples make fun of the Araki’s musical naming convention by using the names of mediocre or one-hit groups familiar to millenials, such as SMASHMOUTH, P.O.D., and ATOMIC KITTEN (upgraded to PUSSYCAT DOLLS). So good.</li>
</ul>

<p>Inevitably there are also a large number of uncreative JoJo reaction and commentary videos, none worth highlighting save for  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mk02Uuex2js">this guy</a> who watched all 43 episodes of Stardust Crusaders in one increasingly nightmarish sitting.</p>

<p>What else? Here’s:</p>

<ul>
  <li>a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ND3TjMx_pwU">woman risking musculoskeletal catastrophe</a> performing a series of JoJo poses.</li>
  <li>Jotaro and DIO’s confrontation re-edited so that they’re playing UNO (there’s also one where Joseph plays connect 4 with villain D’Arby the Elder)</li>
  <li>a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q-Lddkd4vTM">compilation of Engrish speech in JJBA</a>. Laughing at Engrish is perhaps poor form, but in this case it feels like the JJBA voice actors were deliberately hamming it up. I dunno, you decide.</li>
</ul>

<p>What am I trying to convey with this scattershot aggregation? I’d like to say this all summed to something profound, but really I’m just sharing a bunch of vids I like. But I may as well suggest that these videos demonstrate that JJBA provides material of sufficient richness that fans can pick it up and run with it, with results that frequently rival the source “text” for entertainment value. JJBA is hardly the only “property” to get this sort of treatment, but I would rather watch fan-created JoJo material than fan-created Star Wars material. Oh my word yes.</p>

<h1 id="my-favourite-part-and-jojo">My favourite part and JoJo</h1>

<p>To my mind (and I suspect to most others’) the best JoJo part is Diamond is Unbreakable. My favourite, however, is Battle Tendency. Diamond is Unbreakable is unquestionably more sophisticated, but I find Battle Tendency more straightforwardly <em>fun</em>. I concede that picking a Hamon-era JJBA story as my favourite is a bit of a hipster move, but that seems to be how things are.</p>

<p>It follows that my favourite JoJo is Battle Tendency’s Joseph Joestar. This is indeed so, but I like him not so much for his cocky antics in that part, but his changing roles in Parts III and IV. He’s the only JoJo who ages significantly, and while Jotaro turns out to be the lynchpin for the latter half of the parts 1-6 super arc, Joseph is perhaps the most curious and singular of the JoJos. Well, that’s my attempt at serious analysis, but in truth I think this compilation of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=P-3GOo_nWoc">Joseph screaming in Engrish</a> at the absurdist horrors in Part 3 better encapsulates what I like about him.</p>

<p>For what it’s worth Araki reckons Josuke (not sure if part IV Josuke or part VIII Josuke) is his favourite. And for all that I’ve banged on about Joseph, there’s probably thousands of fans who think that insipid (to me at least) Giorno is the best. <em>shrug</em></p>

<figure>
    <img src="/assets/jjba/battle-tendency-gang.jpg" width="600" alt="Battle Tendency gang" title="Battle Tendency gang" />
    <figcaption>The Battle Tendency gang. Credit: <a href="https://jojowiki.com/JoJo_Wiki">Jojo's Bizarre Encyclopedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<h1 id="an-attempt-to-sum-it-all-up">An attempt to sum it all up</h1>

<p>Taking a step back from my Jojomania, I’d have to characterise the phenomenon as style over substance, but JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure has so much style that it sort of becomes the substance. Maybe, if that’s not circularly glib?</p>

<p>To be serious for a minute I would say that JJBA has provided me with a kind of existential solace - many’s a time I’ve been faced with work problems and imagined responding by bellowing “STAR PLATINUM!”, and punching my computer screen. It’s a thought that never fails to cheer me up.</p>

<p>Well, whether or not that makes any sense, I can definitely say JoJo’s Bizarre Adventure is a lot of silly, goofy fun, and I highly recommend it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction]]></summary></entry></feed>